[ Silence ]
[ Music &amp; Background Noise ]
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Ladies and gentlemen,
please welcome Senior Director
OS X Platform Experience Andreas
Venter [assumed spelling].
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Good afternoon.
Welcome to WWDC 2013.
The epic ecosystem continues to
thrive for hundreds of millions
of users enjoying their
iPhones, iPads and Macs.
This morning, we had
several great announcements
that will make our
users even happier.
Starting of course with
iOS 7, the big theme
of iOS 7 is its beautiful
new look.
And it also contains
features like control center
and multi-tasking
UI and AirDrop.
OS X Mavericks is a
very compelling mix
of infrastructure improvements
that lower power consumption,
increase responsiveness.
Together, let's [inaudible]
user features
like margin monitor
support and file tagging
and of course our new maps
and iBooks applications.
Now, what we didn't
tell you this morning is
that we also have big news
on our developer tools.
In addition to our
operating systems,
we're also announcing
a major new version
of Xcode today, version 5.
[ Applause ]
Yeah.
The most important purpose
of Xcode 5 is of course
to let you take advantage
of all the new APIs in iOS 7
and OS X Mavericks, so
that you can get the most
out of these operating systems.
But it also contains
features that will allow you
to create higher quality apps
with a really strong-focus
on testing and debugging.
And all of this gets
surfaced in a fresh new look
that simplifies the
Xcode experience.
This is the new Xcode 5.
Everything is more
compact and clear.
With fewer distractions from
your source code, you're going
to see quite a bit about the new
Xcode 5 throughout this session.
But for now, I'm going to focus
a little more on our agenda
with platform ecosystem.
One of the major forces
that prepares our
platforms is the continued
and growing success
of our app stores.
Just recently, we
crossed this amazing mark
of over 50 billion
app downloads.
And the rate of downloads
start accelerating
because they're constantly
working
on improving our app
store experience.
This year, we're making
it easier for users
to discover new apps through
our apps [inaudible] feature
which crowd-sources relevant
apps that you might want
to use based on your location.
So for example, you can
find apps that's specific
to a shopping mall
you're entering,
or a sports event you're
attending or an area
that you're visiting
as a tourist.
You're also significantly
improving our volume purchase
program which allows
companies and schools
to initiate mass purchases
of app licenses for both iOS
and Mac and to distribute
those licenses to their users
with the help of MDM service.
And for you developers, we're
improving our purchase receipts.
We're now encrypting through
receipts on both platforms,
and via extending the data, you
can access from these receipts.
The concrete example that is
really useful is if you're
in the process of
moving your app
from a paid app to be a premium.
In which case, you can
validate with the receipts
which users have already
paid in full for these apps
and credit them [inaudible]
app purchases you might want
to offer for free.
[ Applause ]
So taking it all together,
they are making improvements
for our end users
for enterprises
and schools and for developers.
And all these features
work together
to make the app store
experience even more compelling
that we're adding
to the business opportunities
they offer to you
as third-party developers.
I'd also like to give you a
very brief update on iCloud.
iCloud provides a
set of services
that integrate seamlessly
with applications
so that users can access
their documents, their media,
and their app data from any
device they choose to work on.
And it's a huge success
for hundreds
of millions of users worldwide.
iCloud also offers a
set of developer APIs
that users can use to integrate
these services with your apps.
Now, we understand that there
is one specific area that many
of you have struggled
to get to work right.
And that is our documents in
the Cloud API with core data.
So this is an area
that we have decided
to not implement any new
features this year but instead
to focus on reliability
and quality.
We have fixed a ton of
perks in this space.
[ Applause ]
We've also made it
easier for you
to interact with
this technology.
We're adding specific iCloud
debugging tools to Xcode 5.
[ Applause ]
You'll be able to use
the key-value store
and the Document API from the
simulator for better testing.
And in case your users -- in
case if users ever need a way
to reset their Cloud data, we
would give them a way to do just
that later this year
on icloud.com.
So, that's just a
brief update on iCloud.
We're working very hard to
getting this right this time,
please try that one more time.
[ Applause ]
All right, for the
remainder of this session,
we're going to take a look
at how our new products
impact your apps.
You already got a good
idea for what they bring
to the table this morning
in the keynote for end users
and at this session, they're
going to focus on what they --
what this all means
for you as developers.
We're going to start
with iOS 7, and for that,
I'm going to bring Toby
Paterson up on stage.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Good afternoon.
We've been working for
quite a while on iOS 7
and I'm really excited to
tell you a bit about it today.
We've got a lot of new
things for you here.
Just for fun, we took a
look and counted the number
of new symbols in our
public frameworks.
We've got 114 new
classes, 679 new methods
and 917 new properties.
Wow! All right, we'll take
that for what it's worth.
But the bottom-line here
is that we've got a lot
of new things for
you to dig into.
Right now though, I want to
talk about just one thing.
The new user interface,
the visual changes
that we've made are of course
the most obvious difference.
But it goes much
deeper than that.
This is not just a facelift.
We broke down all
of our applications
and reassembled them,
focusing first on the content
and then building the
chrome around that.
The result is a fundamental
change to our user experience
that will affect
all applications.
This is not something
that we undertook lightly.
We took a very serious and
measured approach to this.
And there are three big ideas at
the heart of our redesigned UI.
The first of these,
clarity is all
about showing what's relevant.
It means presenting data to
users in a way that makes sense.
Providing features which
are self-explanatory
and discoverable and
providing a consistent
and cohesive user experience
across your applications.
Deference can be
summed up simply
as getting the chrome
out of the way.
Your users care about their
content, their videos,
their messages, their music.
The user interface
should not compete
with that for their attention.
This is perhaps the
most radical change
that we've made in the new UI.
And I think that
new understated look
of iOS 7 will really allow the
personality of your applications
to shine through far
more than ever before.
Now, although we've
simplified the user interface,
that doesn't mean
that it's static.
iOS 7 has tremendous vitality
through the use of
depth and motion.
Parallax blurs and translucency
take the place of gradients
and shadows and cut-lines in
defining your content areas.
And sophisticated animations
make this perhaps the most
lifelike of the any
iOS release yet.
Take a look at the
use of Parallax
on the home screen here.
Notice how the background
appears behind the application
icons and the badge
appears to float above it.
So what does this mean for you?
There are four things that
you need to pay attention to.
The first of these are changes
to the way your content
is laid out.
We have some new metrics on
our system controls and buttons
and pickers have a new look
and a new behavior about them.
I'd like to give you
a quick demo now.
I'm going to walk through
some of the applications
that Craig showed you this
morning, and just point
out some things that we think
you should pay attention to.
Let's go into photos here.
And right away, you can
see some differences.
Let's try this one
and there we go.
Okay, let's go into photos here.
Right away, you can see
some big differences.
Take a look at the bars
at the top and the bottom.
Gone are the gradients
and the shadows
and we've got a much more
muted understated look.
If I drill into some content
here and start scrolling,
take a look closely at the
bars at the top and the bottom.
You can see some of your
content just sort of hinting
through the bar there.
The bars are partially
translucent
and we put a heavy blur on them
so that the text on the buttons
on your bars remain legible.
If you take a look at the
buttons in the navigation bar,
the Back button on the left and
the Select button on the right,
you'll notice also that they
don't have any borders anymore.
Let me select a couple of
photos here and have a look
at the buttons at the bottom.
They too have no boarders.
And in fact, you'll notice
that we're starting to use text
in place of icons in some
place for greater clarity.
Now this is not something
special to photos.
We actually made this change
throughout the system.
Let's go into mail now, and
we'll see here a message
that I was reading earlier.
As I scroll up, you can
see the content showing
through the bars as well.
And here too the
buttons have no borders.
Now, this begs a very important
question, how is the user meant
to know what to tap on?
Well, we're using color in place
of borders to indicate things
that are tappable or can
otherwise be interacted with.
In the case of mail
here, the color is blue
but every application
has its own personality.
And so you can tailor
the tint color
to your application's theme.
Let's go back up to
the message list.
There's one more thing
I want to show you here.
I'm going to swipe on a message
and tap the More button to bring
up the action sheet, and
take a look at the buttons
up in the navigation bar now.
You'll notice that
they've lost their color
because of course
I can't tap on them
because the action sheet is up.
If I just missed the action
sheet, the color goes away.
And this is not just a
simple dimming effect.
We're actually desaturating the
tint color of the control there.
What's happening
under the covers is
that UIKit is changing the tint
color on the inactive controls
and posting a notification.
You can listen for that
notification in your app
so that you can update the color
of your controls accordingly.
And I have a small
confession to make.
My eyes aren't what they used
to be and I'm having a bit
of trouble reading
the text in mail here.
So, I want to show you a
new text-sizing feature
that we've added to iOS 7.
I'm going to switch
into settings here
and you can see right here.
This is a great example of the
new group style Table View.
This is the case where we've
changed some of the metrics.
You'll notice the cells are
now going edge-to-edge instead
of being inset into
rounded racks.
Let's drill into general
and text size and you'll see
that I've got a slider here.
I can drag it to the left to
make text smaller or drag it
to the right to make text
larger in applications
which adopted this feature.
I'm going to leave it on the
right in the largest setting
and switch back through
multi-tasking to mail.
And you can see that mail is
now using a much larger font
and it's also adapted to
the layout of the cells
to accommodate the larger text.
This is a place where I think
Auto Layout Constraints are
really going to help you in your
application with this feature.
Now, I'm having so
much fun up here
that I worry the session
may go a little bit late.
Let's check the calendar
and see if that's going
to cause any problems.
Sure enough, we've got the
Apple Design Awards coming
up a little bit later.
We better do something
about that.
I'm going to tap into the awards
event and edit it and I'm going
to tap on the start time here
to push it back a little.
Notice how the picker slides
or notice how the
Table View slides open
to reveal the new picker.
Once I've changed the time to
push it back or we don't need
to go to 6, I think
5 will be fine.
I'm going to tap the Start
Time to accept my action
and the Table View slides
closed to hide the picker.
This is a new way of using
pickers which will take a bit
of work in your code to adopt it
but I think the result
is a much lighter weight,
easier to use control.
Okay, let's go back
to the slides now.
I want to recap briefly some
of the things we've
just talked about.
So first, your content
needs to go full screen now.
We've always had
translucent bars in UIKit.
The difference now is that
all bars are translucent all
the time.
If your content is in the scroll
view, we can dynamically resize
that and set the content
insets appropriately for you.
If your content isn't
in a scroll view,
you'll have to do a
little bit of work
to adopt for the new layout.
Buttons have no borders anymore
whether you're using a UI button
with a now horribly misnamed
bordered bar button item.
The borders are gone.
[ Laughter ]
And we're using tint
color to indicate things
that can now be interacted
with or tapped on.
Group style Table Views and
some of our new controls or some
of our controls have
new metrics.
Now, we tried very hard to
minimize the number of places
where we did this because
we're fully cognizant
of the impact this will have in
the layout of our application.
Those places where we did do it,
we felt were absolutely
essential
to the goals of the
redesigned UI.
And finally, a new way
of using pickers in line.
So those are some of the things
that have change in UIKit.
The thing to bear in
mind is the vast majority
of the kit remains the same.
I'd like to talk a little
bit now about some new things
that we've added to help you
in your applications adopt
the new principles of design.
Let's start with typography.
Retina devices permit this
incredible quality of text.
What's been missing are some
of the more advanced ideas
in typography that come from
the printed publishing world.
The first of these are kerning
and ligatures which we turned
on by default in text throughout
the system whether using UIKit
or WebKit.
Now, for those of you wondering
what kerning and ligatures mean,
kerning is when two letters
overlap each other such as the T
and the R at the
start of truffle.
And ligatures tie letters
together such as the F, F,
and L at the end of the word.
This might strike some of you
as a rather esoteric point.
But it's one of those
little details that we
at Apple find so important.
I think the result is text
that's much more legible
and frankly more beautiful.
We even support some of
the more extreme cases
out there such as Zapfino.
Another thing that
we've added is a new way
of working with the system font.
Instead of a single
one-type-fits-all system font,
we've introduced a family of
fonts that are being chosen
by our designers to work
well with each other.
We looked at text across
all of our applications
and classified them
into a series
of usage categories or styles.
And for each of those styles,
we chose a specific font
and size relative to each other.
Now typically, if you wanted
to present more information
on the line or make
text more readable,
you would just scale
the font down
or scale it up appropriately.
The problem with that is that it
can leave text very hard to read
at the smaller sizes or
your letters can be big
and blocky at the larger sizes.
So, we're introducing a
new way of sizing text.
You saw me demonstrate
this in mail just now.
We actually changed the
stroke width and the character
in the line spacing of text
at each of the relative sizes.
There's a new API on UIKit
that were turned use --
the specific font to use
for a given size and style.
And WebKit makes
this available to you
through the use of
CSS font values.
We're calling this dynamic type.
It's a very -- we think it's
a very advanced typography,
set of typography features
that we're giving to you
in a mobile operating system.
We think it's pretty cool.
Another thing that
we've added is Text Kit.
Text Kit is an advanced text
and layout rendering engine.
It's a great compliment
to WebKit for those times
where you want to use code to
control the layout of your text.
We took the Cocoa Text
technology from OS X
and brought it to iOS in the
form of a new set of APIs.
Those of you who are familiar
with Cocoa Text will have
no problem using these APIs.
For the most part,
they're the same.
And that's it for text.
Let's talk about animations now.
There are generally three ways
that we sort of group animations
when we talk about them.
Transitions are canned
animations
between your view
controllers, for example.
Motion effects tie animations
to the movement of the device.
And dynamics are animations
that interact with the user.
Let's dig into these a little.
So out of the box, we
write a standard set
of view controller transitions.
Your view slide up
from the bottom
when you present them
modally or from right to left
when you push them on to
a navigation controller.
Well, we're opening
that up to you now
so that you can define your own
animations for a transition.
If you want to flip your
view around when you push it
on to a navigation
controller, for example.
We're also making it easy for
you to tie your animations
to the system transition so that
you can animate alongside one
of the system transitions
or kick off a set
of animations at the end.
UI motion effects.
So as I said before,
motion effects tie movement
of the device to
changes in your UI.
You're familiar with
core motion.
Well we took that and packaged
it up in an easy to use API,
that we're calling
UIMotionEffects.
We take the event
string from core motion
and we crunch the numbers and
convert that into a series
of perspective changes.
We then feature those
perspective changes
so that you can adapt
your UI accordingly.
This is how we implement
the Parallax effect
on the Home screen and
the new tab UI in Safari.
And finally, I'd like to talk
a bit about UIKit dynamics.
I asked one of my engineers for
a succinct description of this,
and he's a smart guy, a doctor.
And this is what he told me.
I had to think about this
one for a little bit.
And I think I can sum it up
a little more simply for you.
We built a physics
engine into UIKit.
So the idea is that the
physics engine deals in terms
of real world type behaviors
-- collisions, gravity,
forces, that kind of thing.
You associate a set of behaviors
with using your hierarchy.
And as the physics engine
runs, it updates properties
on your views and changing
that frame orientation.
Conversely, if you change
properties on your view, say,
in response to the user
swiping across the screen,
we feed those back into the
physics engine and it runs
until -- I'm sorry, it runs
until it come back
to an equilibrium.
This is a super powerful
system that lets you --
makes it very easy to compose
sophisticated interactions
with users.
That's what we call
UIKitDynamics.
Let's talk about
images a little bit.
In the beginning, it
was really simple.
You created your image, you gave
it a name, and you looked it up.
Well then we added iPad
and we needed a way
of differentiating your iPad
art from your iPhone art.
And so we came up with a clever
way of mangling the filename.
Well then we added Retina
iPhones and we need a new way
of differentiating your iPhone
high-res art from your 1x art.
And then we added
Retina iPad, so frankly,
it all just start
getting out of control.
We were running out of ways
of mangling your filenames.
With iOS 7, we are
ending the insanity.
[ Applause ]
We've got a great new UI in
Xcode that makes it really easy
to manage your images.
You can tell at a glance if
you're missing some Retina art,
and we've integrated
this tightly with UIKit.
You still look up your
images the same way
that you've been
doing it for years,
and it's a little
bit faster to boot.
I'd like to invite Max Drukman
on stage now to give you a demo
of this and some other cool
new features in Xcode 5.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thank you Toby.
Can we switch to the
demo machine please?
Welcome to Xcode 5.
Now as Andreas told you, Xcode
5 is much cleaner and lighter
and does a really good job
of keeping your content
front and center.
You'll see a lot more of
Xcode 5 in this session,
but for right now, I'm
going to talk to you
about two new features, Asset
Catalogs, that's the feature
that gets rid of that
naming convention for you,
and the totally revamped
Auto Layout.
Let's have a look.
Here's a game project
I'm working on.
I'm going to dive right
in to the intro screen.
Here I have a couple of buttons
and it's fairly typical
in a game project.
I'm using UIKit buttons but I'm
styling them with custom art.
Since there are only two
buttons on this screen,
I think I'll make
them as big as I can.
And I'm going to push
them over to the side
and I'll make this one
really, really wide.
And here we see that's one of
the pitfalls of using custom art
with a scalable button.
I made my button big but my
artwork got all distorted.
Now, I know what most of you are
already saying to yourselves,
I know how to fix that problem.
You need to get art that's
sliced into three parts.
Well, you're absolutely right
and I appreciate you bringing
that up because it gives me
just the segue way I need
to start talking
about Asset Catalogs.
I'm going to navigate to the
Asset Catalog in my project.
And here we are.
On the left is an outline
with all of the visual assets
of my project and on the
right, there's a thumbnail view
that keeps all of my assets
and their variants organized.
Here we can see the background
of the screen I was just on,
that sort of lime color, with
both the 1x and 2x variants.
The next screen over, the sort
of stone color, also 1x and 2x.
And even my app icon
and launch images
with their five representations.
That's right.
As Toby told you, gone
are the days of the -427K
at 1x twiddle i something.
Naming convention, now we
can all go back to the foo,
bar and baz convention
that we all love so well,
or no convention at all because
the Asset Catalog keeps your
image reps organized for you,
it doesn't really matter what
you name your images anymore.
Let's go back to
my orange buttons.
Now as we know, we need
these in three parts.
Well, one of the features
of the asset catalog editor
in Xcode 5 is that you can
now do slicing right in Xcode.
[ Applause ]
That's right.
I'm going to click the Show
Slicing button down here
in the bottom of the editor.
And here we see the
slicing UI with the 1x
and 2x representations of my art
blown up so we can see pixels.
I can even zoom in
a little more.
Now, all I need to do is
click the Start Slicing button
and I'm given three choices.
I can slice in three parts
so that my image can scale
horizontally, or in three parts
so it can scale vertically,
or of course in nine parts
so that it can scale both
horizontally and vertically.
Somebody out there wins a prize.
I only need mine to
scale horizontally,
so I'm going to choose that.
Now, Xcode analyzed my image
and found the best place
to put the slice points.
[ Applause ]
So I have a left cap, a right
cap, and one pixel of stretch.
The grayed out area
won't be used.
Now, of course, you can
make your own decisions
and change the width of
the caps if you want.
You can even change the
width of the center portion
and it will repeat
rather than stretch.
But I like what Xcode gave me,
so I'm going to slice the 1x
in exactly the same way.
And now, when I use the back
button to go to my story board,
my art is doing the right thing.
[ Applause ]
And now, even when I
scale the other one,
everything is looking great.
Now, let's talk about
Auto Layout.
Obviously, I'm designing
my interface
in the landscape orientation.
But what happens when my
user rotates her device
to see it in portrait?
I need to know what
my interface is going
to do when that happens.
Now, of course, I can
run my app in a simulator
or run a device if
I have one handy.
But we've made it
even easier in Xcode 5
because we've added
a preview assistant.
The preview assistant allows
you to look at your story boards
under different visual
conditions.
So here, I'm designing
in landscape,
but previewing in portrait.
I can essentially design in
two orientations at once now.
And you can see that I have
an Auto Layout problem.
Of course, these demos always
start with a problem, right?
Now, notice that my buttons are
clipped off and they're kind
of floating in the
center somewhere.
But my background and
the logo of my game,
they're actually
doing the right thing.
That's because of a
big change we've made
to Auto Layout in Xcode 5.
Now while you're working
with your interfaces,
you no longer need to have
every object constrained.
[ Applause ]
Yeah, that's got to
be worth something.
It makes it really easy
to work iteratively
through your interfaces
without Auto Layout,
well, getting in your way.
Yeah. Now, we didn't
stop there though.
We've also added a lot
of different ways
to make constraints.
Let me show you my favorite.
Control drag.
I'm going to constraint this
button by control dragging
from it to its superview.
[ Applause ]
Well, wait.
I can even make more than
one constraint at a time.
And now the preview assistant
updates, so I see that I'm
on the right track and
I know that I only need
to make one more constraint,
and now my button is
doing the right thing
in both orientations.
[ Applause ]
There's one more thing.
Now, doing the other
button is even easier.
I can control drag to
the other button and set
up all three constraints
at once.
In one gesture, and
that's pretty simple.
Now --
-- let's look at
this next view over.
It's obviously having
some layout difficulties.
That's because there are no
constraints in this view at all.
Now, control drag is great for
setting up one, two, three,
a handful of constraints, but
of course, you can do things
like select all of the objects
in this view and add all
of the constraints at once.
And you get immediate
feedback that it worked.
That's pretty good.
[ Applause ]
Now let's look at one of
these tab views I have
over here featuring the great
new iOS 7 look and feel.
Now as I said, you
can have the assistant
in a different orientation
like, you know, I can go back
and forth between
landscape and portrait.
I can have different
device sizes so I can --
here I'm switching between the
three and a half and four inch.
I can even go back and
look at iOS 6.1 style UI.
[ Applause ]
And we see that my constraints
are doing the right thing.
They're -- it's --
they're reacting perfectly
to orientation change, device
sizes, and even iOS versions.
And I get to see immediately,
thanks to the assistant,
that I'm doing the right thing.
Thank you.
Back to you Toby.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; So there really
is so much more
in iOS 7 than just one thing.
The new multitasking
interface, for example.
It really shows off the
user's running applications.
This makes it all the more
important than your app --
that your app's content is as
up to date as you can make it.
To help you out, we're
adding three ways for you
to update your application's
content in the background.
With background fetch, we
will run your application
periodically so that you
can pull new data down
and update your UI accordingly.
If your server --
[ Applause ]
-- if your server
has a minimum time
between connection attempts,
you can use this API to tell us
when it would be
inappropriate to run you.
With remote notifications, we'll
run your application in response
to a push notification so that
you can update your content
on demand versus having to pull.
[ Applause ]
And with background transfers,
we make it easy for you
to upload or download your
data in the background even
if your application
isn't running.
You simply create an NSURL
session and we take care
of transferring the
data for you.
Now, I've been told I'm
not actually allowed
to push back the start time
of the Apple Design Awards,
and there's really too much for
me to cover up on stage here.
We have a lot of sessions
and labs this week
and I know a number
of my engineers are
up here to talk with you.
So how should you get
started with this?
Well, first of course, download
the SDK, build your application,
and boom, you've got
the new user interface.
You may need to update
your UI to accommodate some
of the changes that
we've talked about,
but we really encourage you to
actually take a deeper rethink
on the design of your
UI along the lines
of what we've done in iOS 7.
Let's take a look at these
numbers again from this morning,
93 percent of our users are
running the latest iOS release.
That's pretty incredible.
We think it won't be very long
after all before
the vast majority
of your users are running iOS 7.
We've got some great
documentation on the web,
and I encourage you to download
the iOS 7 UI Transition Guide
available at this URL here.
If you can type that
one quickly.
And that's it for iOS 7.
Now, games are a very important
category of application.
And to talk about some
exciting new stuff,
I'd like to hand
off to Jeff Stone.
Jeff?
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thanks Toby.
So we have some really great
new game technology to talk
about today, first let's do an
update -- update on Game Center.
Apple's social gaming network,
we introduced it three years ago
and it's doing amazingly well
with 240 million players.
Of course, Game Center supports
things like leaderboards
and multiplayer challenges
and friends.
And we're going to
continue to enhance it.
Now leaderboards, you can
have over 500 leaderboards,
you can have up to
500 leaderboards.
We have modal challenges that
allow you to tie a challenge
to a specific mode of your game.
And we have -- we have turn --
you can add to turn-based
applications either auctions
or in-game trading
among other things.
But the big news today is
we have two new technologies
to introduce that makes
game development easier
and better than ever.
First, I want to
introduce Sprite Kit.
So if you're building a game
like one of our iconic games
on the platform, Cut the
Rope, Where's My Water,
or Jetpack Joyride, you need
to spend time building
a good game engine.
And to build a good game
engine, it takes a lot
of knowledge to do that.
So we thought, what can we do
to help you game developers
make your life easier?
So that's why we
created Sprite Kit.
It has everything you
expect in a game engine.
It has a great animation
system, particles, physics,
image effects, video tie-in,
and all that and more.
It's high performance with --
at its core is a
high-performance rendering
engine built by people
who really know GPU
development inside and out.
We have integrated tools in
Xcode and it's easy to learn,
which means you have
less code to write.
Let us do the heavy lifting for
you and so you can concentrate
on building a great game.
And of course, it's available
for both iOS and OS X,
which means the code you write
can be used on both platforms.
So let's take a look at a demo.
[ Applause ]
So here's a little tour of some
of the features of Sprite Kit.
First, obviously, is
an animation system.
The animation system has all
the things you would expect --
translation, rotation,
scaling, fade in, fade out,
and these actions can
be chained together --
chained together or combined
and run in parallel in groups.
Oops, let's try that again.
This is also optimized
for both --
for OS X and iOS hardware
with the added benefit
that it makes it really
battery-efficient.
So that -- so that's
the animation system.
Next is physics.
We obviously -- we have
integrated physics.
But this is not just, we provide
physics alongside of Sprite Kit,
we actually have
integrated physics.
Putting physics into your
application is as simple
as one API call for
setting the physics body.
So we can -- we can kind
of lean one direction
or we can go back the other way,
and also we can obviously
put some touch events
in to add some impulses
to our physics engine.
Really efficient physics
engine built into Sprite Kit.
The -- next, particles.
We have full particle system
in there, 37 properties
of these particles, and the key
here is you can either modify
these with your code
or you can --
or you can modify the data
which means you can
build particles offline
and archive them for
use by your application.
We also have an interpolated
spawning [phonetic] system
which we think of this as
an anti-clumping technology.
As I move this around, you
see the particles are evenly
distributed in the trail.
Everything like that, all of
this 60 frames per second,
I can even write with it.
Here you go.
We've also integrated Sprite Kit
into our existing graphics
technology core image.
So you can apply CI filters
to your application here.
And once we toss
a filter on here,
so you can have this great,
yeah, this great pinch effect
on there as the physics
simulation continues to run.
We have a pixelate filter
on top of the system.
And these filters can be applied
to all or part Sprite tree
and finally a really,
really cool --
-- twirl effect.
So you can apply CI filters
right on top of your scene.
Finally, the video.
We've taken our great
media technologies
and integrated video
in the Sprite Kit.
This means you can
mass the video
and I can manipulate the
mass on top of the video.
And you can combine
this into your scene
such the video is not just for
cut scenes and transitions.
I can add sprites in here.
And you see the sprites fly
in front and behind the video.
Video is a first class
citizen in Sprite Kit.
So that's a quick
tour of Sprite Kit.
[ Applause ]
I thought of making the
game development easier
for all of you.
How else I'm going to do that?
Well, we're going to introduce
comprehensive, full-featured,
production quality game
sample code for you guys.
So let me jump in here
and show you what we have.
So this is our adventure game.
It is a Multiplayer
Dungeon Crawler
with all the features
you would expect.
So it has a multi-directional
scrolling, parallax effects,
we have part of this falling
leaves particle effects
that the enemies have AI,
with high quality art work.
All of this was production
quality code which allows you
to just grab it, and either
start your next game project
with it, or adapt the two, or
pull some technologies out of it
to adapt it to your
current game.
There you go.
So let's jump back in the
Xcode and take a look.
So these samples are made
for both OS X and iOS
which means the vast majority
of the source files are shared,
so you can use them to support
either operating system.
We have over 1,700 art
files in this sample.
And if we go look at the part --
one of the particle
effects here,
this is a leaf particle effect,
what you'll notice is we
build a particle editor right
in the Xcode.
[ Applause ]
So I can change the generation
rate on the particles here.
We take a lot more of leaves --
that that's felt
better for the game.
And, you know, leaves fall in
the fall not when they're green
so we want to change one
of our key colors here.
And we'll make that red.
And we've changed
the particle effect.
Again, this is editing
the particle data
so when you build your
application again,
when you build your game,
it's picked right up
and your game will
have this effect in it.
So that's a quick tour of
one of our new game samples.
[ Applause ]
The next big technology we have
to announce today
is Game Controllers.
[ Applause ]
We're taking the gaming
experience to a new level
by defining the standard --
a common standard for game
controllers that allow high --
that allow all users to have
high quality game controllers.
So how are we doing this?
We are providing the users --
users can pick whatever
third-party controller
they prefer.
Software developers can build a
single software interface rather
than having to support
a multitude
of software interfaces,
thus as game developers,
you can concentrate
in building your game
versus supporting a whole bunch
of different game controllers.
This comes into two parts.
First, a hardware standard,
this is part of our MFi program.
And secondly, a software
interface
which allows software
developers to build --
which allows you to build
to a common interface.
Let's first talk
about the hardware.
The hardware comes
into two types,
either form-fitting
snapping controls,
or your stand-alone controllers.
There's also two configurations.
The standard configuration
has a d-pad, four buttons,
and some shoulder buttons.
The hands configuration adds two
thumb sticks and two triggers.
All inputs are
pressure-sensitive.
And we talked about
high quality.
We want to ensure there are
high quality controllers
to give your users
a great experience,
we do these by requiring
no calibration,
the inputs can't drift,
and all the buttons have
to have the same feel.
Of course there's a
software piece of this.
So you can -- so your software
can communicate directly
with controllers.
And this is, the truth be told,
this is really easy to adopt
with both polling and
callback types of inputs.
We've also designed it
so you can actually use
the Multi-Touch interface
or the gyro in conjunction
with your controller
so you can make a great a hybrid
experience for your users.
And of course this is both
on iOS 7 and OS X Mavericks.
So I think the best way
to show what you can do
with controllers
is to do a demo.
I like to invite Thomas
Schegloff [assumed spelling]
on stage to show
what they've built.
So we do --
[ Applause ]
Last week, we reached out
to Crytek, they're working
on their new iOS application
collectibles and they came in
and integrated game controllers
into their application.
Within a day, they had a
standard controller working.
What you have here is a tactical
action game and this is running
on the iPhone and you can use
the controller using the D-pad
for relative movements
to avoid those explosions
and advance his squad,
as he advances his squad,
he get -- comes under fire.
What he now can do
is hit a button
to move the squad to cover.
He finds that he wants
to directly manipulate
some of his troops.
What he can do is he can use
at the touch interface to touch
on a troop and he can
drag it specifically
to a point he wants
deploy them at.
But this allows a great hybrid
mix of the game controller
and the Direct-Touch interface.
He finds his squad
gets in a little --
[ Applause ]
He finds -- he gets
in a little trouble,
he can hit the shoulder button,
calling some air support,
now the D-pad switches over to
controlling his air support.
Beautiful job, very little time
integrating controller setup
into this game, brilliant
graphics.
Tremendous job by Crytek
and then you can go,
thank you, Thomas.
[ Applause ]
So we want to make you --
get you guys jump-started
on working with controllers.
We've worked with Logitech,
put some standard
snapping controllers
in the labs this week
and they'll be --
so tomorrow, you can head down
to the labs with your code
and get a jump-start
on developing
for controllers integrating
them to your application.
So we've talked about a lot
of things in game development,
two new APIs, Sprite Kit
and game controllers.
Tools built in the
Xcode, particle editor,
and a text [inaudible]
generator.
We have new game samples.
We showed you one
of them, adventure,
we also have a turn
based puzzle game.
These samples are
production quality code,
they're fully documented
and a code displaying cell
documentation allow you --
allowing you to grab that,
use it to start your next
application or take a piece
of technology out of it and add
it to your current application.
So I can't wait to see --
I can't wait to see
what you guys build
with our new game technology
and I'd like to hand it back
over to Andreas to talk
about OS X Mavericks.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thank you Jeff.
Our gaming technologies have we,
come a long way just last year
and I'm already looking forward
to wasting even more of my time
with the new creations
you come up with.
All right.
Let's talk about OS X Mavericks.
So Mavericks, the big
architectural focus area is
optimizing power consumption.
All of us here are already
used to optimizing our apps
for low memory use and
low CPU utilization.
But the majority of computers
used nowadays are laptops
and mobile users really also
care about long battery life.
These added several features to
Mavericks that allows end users
to understand the
power consumption
of the apps they're
using better.
For example, by listing
how are hungry apps
in the battery menu extra
and in activity monitor.
And you probably don't want
your apps to show up there.
[ Laughter ]
The good news is
that the following --
a few very straightforward
rules like not using unnecessary
or too frequent timers, you can
often achieve great results.
This slide here shows
a comparison of OS X,
10.8 and 10.9 running
on the same hardware.
As you can see, just two
software changes, we were able
to squeeze out significant
improvements to battery life
and so can you in your own apps.
Another big focus area
for us was responsiveness
such as the scroll speed of
table use and the smoothness
of animations and switching
between different
application states.
You saw this morning in the key
note how nicely made [inaudible]
and Safari, now react
to user events.
Now one problem is that
optimizing power consumption
and preparing an app for great
responsiveness can sometimes
trade often each other.
So the trick is to
find the right balance,
the right intersection between
power and responsiveness.
Let's take a look at a few
things within the Mavericks
that you believe
represent the right choices.
We implemented new mechanisms
that vastly improved
memory management.
We introduced in our scrolling
architecture in App Kit
and of course we added the new
App Net feature which started,
it's the power consumption
of background with apps.
For memory, we've now
centralized all our management
policies which makes the OS more
efficient and more predictable.
For several releases
already, we have notified apps
if you needed their help
because memory pressure
in the system had
reached the level --
that we needed to free
some extra memory.
But they only notified once we
had already reached a very high
level of memory pressure.
So in general, apps didn't
really know what was going
on around them and
then it was okay again
to become more aggressive.
That's using more memory.
So we're improving this in
two ways and [inaudible].
First of all, they're going
to send you two notifications
why the memory pressure
is increasing.
An early warning and also a
critical level notification.
And then we're also going to
send you an all clear signal
if the memory drops back down
to normal levels then it's okay
for you for example to create
larger in-memory caches again.
So by listening to all
this notifications,
apps can now make much
more informed decisions
about their memory use.
We've also improved all
purgeable memory handling
and made it actually
predictable.
Instead of purging memory based
on age, you now purge based
on the memory pressure
in the system.
And they're allowing apps
to specify more fine-grained
priorities to indicate
which regions are best
to take down first.
Unlike low memory notifications,
purgeable memory is designed
so that the system
can free memory
without unvoiding any apps.
So it's quicker and
it's cheaper.
And with the new behavior,
it is a lot more useful now.
The easiest way for you to
leverage purgeable memory is
through our Libcache
and NSCache APIs.
We've also added a compressor
to the memory management
techniques you now use
in Mavericks.
Instead of swapping out
memory directly to disc,
you're now freeing pages
by compressing them
in an intermediate stage,
which dramatically
improves responsiveness
to memory regress, because
there is no I/O needed.
And if you do have to
swap out to disc later,
we can do so in an asynchronous
fashion that's larger,
more uniformed chunks of memory.
It also has a really nice
side effect of swap --
side effect of swapped
files staying smaller
and less fragmented.
So all this memory management
techniques now work together
in Mavericks to give us the
most efficient memory management
system you've ever had in OS X.
Next, our scrolling
architecture.
To improve responsiveness
of scroll views,
you've completely reinvent
all the scrolling architecture
in AppKit.
To maybe achieve the smooth
scrolling you observed this
morning and in [inaudible]
calendar is
that you're now pregenerating
and buffering additional review
content beyond the visible view
areas and just scrolling
that content with the help
of core animation just makes
it hardware accelerated.
So let's say we have
a scroll view
that shows a portion
of a larger document.
AppKit will now ask
the application
to render extra content
in small chunks
when the system is
otherwise idle?
Notice that we are not
changing the threading model
of AppKit in any way.
All the rendering
still takes place
on the main thread as usual.
But since this happens
in small chunks as long
as your application can render
that content quickly enough
if we never block them in main
thread for long and interfere
with the user in any way.
Also, so that we can easily give
the memory back to the system
in case we get in the
high memory pressure,
they're storing this overdraw
of content in purgeable memory.
Now, when the user
initiates a scored event,
AppKit can respond
immediately [inaudible]
of the available overdraw.
So AppKit will stop
at the attempt scoring
with a perfect 60
frames a second as long
as there are sufficient
overdraw available,
but at the same time
right from the beginning
of the event working with your
app to draw even more content
for the download document.
So chances are that by the time
the scored event has reached
these new areas, the
application is already had time
to finish rendering
those as well.
And the net result is
that became as long
as your application can render
that content quickly
enough often achieve better,
smooth 60 frames a second
for the entire scroll event.
Responsive scrolling
takes effect automatically
for most applications linked
against our latest tested case.
There is no special
adoption required,
but they did add a few
methods to end this view
and in the scroll
view that allow you
to customize the behavior
in case your application
has special needs.
Next, let's talk about App Nap.
The perhaps most
effective way we found
to lower power consumption
of the overall system is
the new App Nap feature.
It focuses system
resources on the user --
on the work that made us the
most to the user right now,
while at the same time
drastically scaling back the
resources being offered to
applications that aren't
as critical to the user
at this point in time.
App Nap takes effect
after a short delay,
but once an application naps if
it see a reduction in priority
for I/O and CPU --
for I/O and CPU time.
And also, maybe most
importantly, if it see any time
as it sets up being
rate limited.
We found that unnecessary, in
two frequent timers and one
of the largest sources
of unnecessary power
drain in the system.
So we are quite aggressive with
our RAID limiting, napping apps,
received events, time events,
only every 10 seconds or so.
And the -- even aligning the
time as of all the napping apps
so that don't end up breaking
up the CPU individually,
but instead perform their work
together at the same time.
To decide whether an
application can nap,
we take a look at manufactures.
The decision is fairly
easy if a user
for example hides
an application.
But the -- even monitoring
things
like drawing activity
of backgrounded apps.
So that applications that are
in the background may
be possibly occluded
by other windows to
-- for you to App Nap
if they don't update the
UI in any visible way.
Another factor we take
into consideration is whether
applications have declared
in power assertions.
This is an area that is going to
be more important going forward.
Applications need
to tell the system
if they are performing any work
that the user still expects
to finish quickly even
if the application is
being backgrounded.
For example, a long
running file export.
And the easiest way
to do that as
to the new NSProcessInfo API
was listed here on the slide.
Now, to show you a little bit
more about how App Nap works,
I'm going to ask
Max Drukman to come
up on stage again
for another demo.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thank you [inaudible].
Can we switch to the
demo machine, please?
All right.
Here is the Mac version of the
game I was working on earlier
and now we can all thrill as
I implement power assertions.
Now, just kidding.
I'm going to show you App Nap
in action and some features
in Xcode 5 of course that
can help you spot performance
problems you might not
have known you had.
We're going to run my app.
Here it is.
But before we look at the
app, let's look at Xcode
and see what it's showing us.
I'm going to zoom in
so we get a good look.
Now, in the debug navigator,
we showed you what we
were calling debug gauges.
There is one each for CPU,
memory and energy impact.
There's super low
overhead and they're great
for spotting problems
with your app.
Here we can see that my app
is taking, well, zero CPU,
the memory is stable and the
energy impact is low to zero.
That means this view in
this app is doing great.
It's a good citizen.
Nothing much to see
here, move along.
But now let me show
you a problem scenario
that in the past was
kind of hard to spot.
I'm implementing a new
feature behind this map button.
And what that does is it allows
my users to bring up a level map
in the game and see where they
are as represented by this pin
in the center as well as
other players around the world
who were playing
on the same level.
Now, the position of the other
players is provided by a server.
There are obviously
aren't any players yet,
I'm still developing here,
but the codes in place
to provide that information.
But if we look back
in Xcode we can see
that there is some trouble.
My CPU and energy impact
gauges have spiked up
and kind of stayed there.
Let's have a closer look.
When you select a
debug gauge in Xcode,
you see its report
in the editor area.
The report gives you the
current status as well as a view
over time and a button that
even allows you to dive directly
into instruments right away
if there's a problem you spot
and wants to deeply analyze.
The memory report is similar
with the current
and overtime views.
Energy impact provides that data
as well as your App Nap status
and various aspects
of power usage.
Each of which has a button
that allows you to analyze
that aspect in the instruments.
Now, let's start with CPU here.
High CPU usage is often
associated with drawing,
but it sure doesn't look like
my app is doing any drawing.
Luckily, Xcode 5 has
given us something
that can help us with that.
We've added Cocoa view debugging
support so I can do something
like turn on view drawing.
And now, every time a view
redraws, I get a highlight.
[ Applause ]
Oh, well, you may be thrilled
by that but of course,
what this tells me is that I
didn't do a very clever thing.
My map pin is redrawing itself
all the time even though it
isn't moving.
The one clever thing I did do,
however, is add a debug menu
so I can turn off draw updating.
There, problem solved.
[ Laughter ]
Now, my CPU is looking good
but my energy impact
is still kind of high.
Let's see if App Nap
helps us with that.
I'm going to maximize Xcode
so that my app is behind
and would -- should
get App Nap to kick in.
Now, on this machine, I've
set App Nap to kick in quicker
than normal and hopefully we're
going to see it any second now.
And, there it goes.
Now, App Nap has done its
thing and my app is now driven
to zero energy usage or almost.
Notice that I'm getting
little blips on the graph.
Now, as Andreas told us earlier,
that's indicative
of a timer firing.
And sure enough, I've
got a timer firing.
Yet another bad pattern.
I've gone with here is that
my app is pulling the server
for user updates instead of
waiting for a notification.
That's not a great
design pattern
but it's one who's impact was
kind of tough to spot before.
After all, I wasn't seeing
poor graphics performance
or beach balling
or my fan spinning.
But that doesn't mean there
wasn't a significant energy
impact going on.
So, even though App Nap does
the right thing for your users,
it really pays to
do the extra work
to make your app also a good
energy citizen whether it's
active or it's napping.
And Xcode 5 gives
you the tools to make
that possible and easy to do.
Back to you, Andreas.
[ Applause ]
Thank you, Max.
There's a few more
APIs and behaviors I'd
like to cover starting with
our new margin monitor support
which makes using [inaudible]
displays even more powerful
and flexible.
Do you think this is going
to work especially great
for all pro-users who often work
with multiple apps
at the same time?
And by the way, it also
works well to the Xcode
that you can run
Xcode on one screen
and the back end application
on the other screen.
Now, we also believe
that the new behavior
to make it more likely that
users will choose to go
into full screen modes.
So now more than ever it's
worth spending the extra time
on implementing a great
full screen experience
in your own apps.
Now, there's a few behaviors you
might have felt like in the past
that don't hold through anymore.
Most importantly, there's no
distinction between primary
and secondary displays.
So, an app cannot assume anymore
that it has the entire
screen available to itself
on another display
because now the doc
and the Menu bar show
up there as well.
You might want to validate
that your apps behave properly
under these new conditions
before we ship Mavericks later
this year.
Another exciting change in
Mavericks is the TVs can now act
as fully independent
displays via AirPlay.
AirPlay is not limited
to mirroring the
primary screen anymore.
That opens up whole new
ways for you to innovate.
If your apps would benefit from
the special presenter display,
AirPlay is now an even
more attractive option.
We're looking very much forward
to the new ideas you guys
are going to come up with
to leverage this new capability.
Next is Map Kit.
If you brought Map
Kit over to the Mac,
that's practically the
identical API that many
of you are already
familiar with from iOS.
So you can now have beautiful
fast vector-based maps
integrated with your
Mac apps as well.
In addition to creating the
actual maps application,
they started using this
new API [inaudible]
in Mavericks in various ways.
For example, by adding
a new data detector,
all by supporting map
locations in the calendar app.
Map Kit is a really fantastic
edition to the OS X API.
And just like with our other
cloud services based APIs,
it's available to apps shipping
through the Mac App Store
that declare the use of
Map Kit as a capability.
Now, there's numerous
more APIs in Mavericks
that I do not have time
to cover in this session.
AppKit has a fantastic
new stack view.
They even added things
like vec notifications.
But you'll also push
notifications to a Mac even
if you don't have a
native application for it.
You can learn about
many of these APIs here
in later sessions
at the conference.
But for now, I'm going to
hand over to Matthew Firlik
to tell you more about Xcode 5.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thank you, Andreas.
Xcode 5 is our latest
tools release
for iOS 7 and OS X Mavericks.
And it is packed with features
I think you guys are going
to love.
From the earlier demonstrations
you've seen Xcode's new clean
interface design.
This design surfaces Xcode's
familiar workflows and features.
It works to minimize clatter
and really put the focus
on the controls and
your content.
To highlight your content,
we'd worked to reduce
the application chrome.
Compared with the
previous release,
our toolbar is 30
percent smaller.
And its work is great
on small displays.
We've also focused on
improving the activity view.
You now see more details for
your activities, bigger icons
for issues, and overall
progress is much easier to see.
And throughout the interface,
you'll see our design focuses
on removing borders, simplifying
items, and through this use
of a simple blue highlight
presenting a feeling
of seamlessness and
fluidity throughout the ID.
Now, a focus on simplicity
does not mean a lost
in functionality, actually
quite to the contrary.
In most cases, we were able
to put more functionality
in a smaller space.
The UI for looking
at project-wide finds is
a really good example.
Comparing a new UI to the
previous release seen here
on the left, you can
see that we were able
to put the same functionality
in less than half of the space.
And in a way that is
far easier to use.
Now, with the additional real
estate, we wanted to bring
to the surface even
more of your content.
In the previous Xcode release,
search results were shown
at a single line displace.
Xcode 5, we're bringing
in wrapping.
So, now, you can see even more
context for your search results.
[ Applause ]
And if that wasn't enough
for bringing the same
display to issues as well.
So for errors and warnings --
[ Applause ]
-- not that that you have
issues, but for all the errors
and warnings that might come
up for all the other guys,
you can see all of the details.
Now, another area of focus
for us is documentation.
And we have a brand
new interface for you.
Documentation is now its own
separate window using all
of the new design elements.
Now, on top of some great
documentation content,
you now have better
and faster searching,
scrollable search results,
tab based browsing,
and a great book marking
system so you can work
with multiple documents
really easily.
[ Applause ]
And if that wasn't enough,
once you find a document
that you like, the
new integrated table
of contents makes it
really easy to browse
and navigate the content.
[ Applause ]
You'll see elements of a new
design throughout our interface,
and it really focuses
on surfacing the value
of the technologies that are
underneath because the same time
that we are changing things
you can see on the front end.
We were doing a lot of work
on the back ends too in ways
that you won't be able to see
but you will definitely feel.
Xcode 5 has been converted
over to Automatic
Reference Counting or ARC.
And as part of this transition,
we have some awesome performance
wins to share with you.
Many of the tasks, new perform
every day, are much faster
in Xcode 5, things
like searching
and incremental builds
are up to twice as fast.
And working with tabs, devices,
and project editor
is quicker than ever.
[ Applause ]
Inside and out, Xcode
5 really sings.
So on top of the new UI
and its great foundation
of faster technologies, we've
built some amazing new features.
And it starts with
interface design.
Xcode 5 provides access to
the latest views and controls
for iOS 7 and OS X Mavericks.
So, you can get started today
using all of these new UIs
and features in your
application.
And, Max demonstrated three new
editions to our design tools.
The new workflow for Auto
Layout, the Asset Catalog,
and the new Preview
Assistant for iOS.
These features in concert
with other editions
to interface builder,
make it easy for you
to design applications
that look and feel great
for all of your users.
Now, Mac still a little
bit of the Thunder 2
and showed you another
great addition to Xcode 5
in the form of debug gauges.
The debug gauges
provide a way for you
to ensure your application is
behaving exactly as you expect.
You now have CPU memory and
other information available
to you at a glance and in a way
that is really easy to track.
The integrative reports
provide even more detail
on the performance
of your application.
So you can dig in
when issues arise.
Now, as Max noted, the gauges
perform high level profiling
in a super efficient manner
so as not to interrupt
with your own applications
performance.
But when you need
more information,
the power of instruments
is just a click away.
We'll launch a session
automatically configured
to your application and
you'll get all the information
you need.
Now we have gauges for CPU,
memory and energy and two others
in the form of iCloud
and OpenGL ES.
And these gauges present
themselves automatically
when you start using
these technologies.
So we think debug gauges are
going to be a great way for you
to monitor, maintain, and
improve the performance
for your applications.
But we didn't stop there
because we have some other great
additions to the
debugging technologies.
First up, our debugging
services.
Xcode provides new functionality
to help you during development.
For example, we can
simulate a backgroundd fetch
for iOS 7 making it really easy
for you to adapt to the new API.
We can also simulate location
changes for iOS and OS X
which are great to use with
colocation and with maps.
And a cocoa view debugging
that Max demonstrated before
is a great way for you
to be interactive
with your application
and see things you might
not been able to before.
Another area of focus for us was
on presentation of variables.
A new variables view is
simple, clean, and compact.
And the improvements of the data
formatters really highlight the
essential information.
But, we know that not all
objects present themselves well
in summary or in textural form.
So for this release we've
integrated a technology
that should be very familiar
to you right in the debugger
in the form of Quick Look.
Now, in the variables
view and in the editor
across every variable, you
will see a Quick Look button.
And in this case, a poke
in the eye is actually
a really good thing.
We now have Quick Look support
for common geometric types
like points, rects,
sizes, and bezier paths.
[ Applause ]
Working with plain or
rich text, super easy.
Media types like images present
themselves really naturally.
Object types like Pads
and URLs actually resolve
to their remote content
whether it's a website
or a local document.
[ Applause ]
And when running
on OS X Mavericks,
locations present themselves
using the gorgeous new map view.
These are just a few
of the Quick Look support
we've innovated in the debugger
and I'm absolutely certain you
guys are going to love this.
So the combination of debug
gauges, debug services,
and the Quick Look for
variables, all great ways
for you guys to get
more information
about your applications.
Now, debugging is generally
about getting your application
into a working state.
In contrast, unit testing is
about keeping it in that state.
We feel that testing is a
really essential component
to writing a great application.
And for this release,
we're providing some new
powerful testing tools
for you to use.
And to show you a
little bit more,
I'm going to give
you demonstration.
[ Applause ]
So here we have the
Adventure project that Max
and I have been working on.
Max has been adding some of
the configuration screens.
I've been working on adding
some new villainous characters
and some additional
game play options.
Now along the way, Max and I
have been writing unit tests
to make sure that
we're staying on track
and then we're not regressing.
And we've been using some
of the new features
of Xcode 5 with that.
One of the new features
I've been using is the new
test navigator.
When I select here on
the left hand side,
the test navigator now
shows you all of the tests
for your project organized by
test class and by test case,
making it really easy for you
to navigate and select an item.
The navigator can show you all
of your tests or just the ones
that are configured for
your current scheme.
Now as you might expect,
I made some changes
to my project right
before coming up on stage.
And I like to see how I'm doing.
So we'll go ahead and
perform the test command here
and see the results.
And you can see that
the status for all
of my tests is now displayed
in the test navigator.
All of the passing
tests are in green
and the failing tests
are in red.
We can see I have a couple red
icons here so we know that --
I probably shouldn't check
this code in quite yet.
Let's select one of
the failing tests.
This test is testing that
the chase radius for one
of my anime characters
is actually larger
than the character himself,
seems to make sense.
I'd like to actually
debug this test
to figure out why it's failing.
And to do that, I'm going to
use a new feature of Xcode 5.
I'll put a breakpoint
in my test.
But in order to just
work on this one test,
I'll hover over this indicator.
And you'll see it turns
into a play button.
This gives me the ability
to run just this one test.
[ Applause ]
Actually, this feature
is even cooler.
Anywhere you see this
status icons you get the
same functionality.
So if I clicked on the icon
at the class level it
would perform all the tests
in the class at the
bundle level, all the tests
with a bundle and so forth.
For this case, I just
want to run this one test.
So I click here, and
it's going to build
and now I'm stopped
here right into my test.
To debug this a little further,
I want to get some information
on the variables to make sure
that the values are as I expect.
I'll hover over the
chase radius here
and if you can look really
closely, a little tool that pop
up showing that that the value
is 8,000, that's correct,
that's what I expected to be.
Let's take a look
at this next piece.
I have an image for
the character.
I want to make sure
that it's the right one.
I'll hover over it and click
the little Quick Look icon
and there we go.
There is a picture of my boss.
[ Applause ]
Actually, I want to
clarify a second.
I said that's a picture
of my boss.
It's not actually a picture
of my boss, it's picture
of the character in the game.
All right.
Let's move on.
I can also check the size
of the character is correct
and that looks right.
You know what?
I see the problem here.
It's actually just
a logic error.
I use greater than
instead of less than.
So let me fix that and
remove my breakpoint.
And let's run the test
again to make sure
that that fix is correct.
And sure enough,
my test succeeds,
the indication is updated and
now I know that I can move on.
So just like that I was able
to use the navigator to get
to my tests that are failing,
used the status indication
in your workflows to
focus on this one test.
Now, we've seen the navigator,
I have some other failing tests.
They're little bit strewn
out across my project.
I'm going to turn on
the filter at the bottom
of the test navigator to show
me only the failing tests.
Now, I see here that I
have three or four tests
that look all the same and
are failing in a similar way.
Earlier, I added some new
functionality to the game,
a new way for anime characters
to meet their maker,
so to speak.
It's affectionately known
as splort [phonetic].
You can imagine what it does.
To test for this, I first
look for the characters health
to be non-zero beforehand,
tell them to splort
and then test afterwards
to see that is zero.
This test is failing.
Now the test itself
is relatively simple,
so it's probably
somewhere in my AppLogic.
That's okay, we can take a look.
I'll command click on the
API to jump right to it.
And this kind of highlights
are really interesting scenario
where sometimes you'll
be working on your tests
and sometimes you'll
be working on your API.
But often you want to
correlate between the two.
To make sure you're
making decisions correctly
on both sides.
Xcode 5 provides a really
great way to do this.
Let's collapse the navigator
to give ourselves
a little more room.
With -- my focus inside of
this method, I'm going to click
on the related files
pop-up here and we'll see
that there are two
new categories.
Test classes and test colors.
I'm going to hold on the Option
key and select the test colors,
and have it opened up
in the assistant editor.
Now, what is this showing me?
It's showing me on the
left hand side my API.
And the right hand side,
it's showing the tests
that directly call that API.
Making it really easier
for me to correlate.
And actually, this is
really helpful in this case
because I see that my test
is testing for health,
but I don't actually
use that value any
over here in my actual method.
And it turns out
that's my fault.
What I forgot to do
was to call super,
when I implemented this method.
So let's go ahead and fix that.
And while I'm still
in the assistant here,
I'll just run my other tests.
Sure enough, that was the fix.
We'll use the power of this
system here to just flip
to the next one and make sure
that that one is fixed too and,
yep that was my problem.
So just like that, I was able
to correlate my API and my tests
and work with them
together to fix my problem.
So that was just a
quick view of some
of the great new testing
features in Xcode 5.
Let's go back to slides.
[ Applause ]
So the new unit testing features
of Xcode, the test navigator,
the assistant editor, and the
new workflow integrations,
all great ways for you to
make testing a seamless part
of your development workflow.
Now, another investment for
us in the area of testing was
in the test framework itself.
And for this release,
we are announcing a
new framework XC test.
XC test is derived from OCUnit.
And for this release we've
made some minor enhancements.
Going forward, XC test
will be our vehicle
for providing great
testing features for you.
Now Xcode 5 continues
to include OC unit
and it includes a powerful
migration utility for you
to convert over whenever
you're ready.
Now, from all the
feedback you've provided,
the number one request
you've had in the area
of testing is better
ways to integrate it
into your automation systems.
And with Xcode 5, we have
a great new option for you
in the form of command
line testing.
[ Applause ]
I didn't know a terminal
window is so exciting.
The test command is now fully
supported from the command line.
And this command mirrors the
test action inside of the IDE.
So, your investment in
setting up your schemes
and your test plans now pay
off beautifully inside the IDE
and out.
The command allows you
to specify the destination
you'd like.
So, for example, you can
target one of the simulators.
As you might expect, you can
also target a connected device.
And, as a little
gift to you guys,
you can also specify
multiple destinations
in a single invocation.
[ Applause ]
So we think this is going
to be a great addition
for all of your workflows.
Apple IDs.
Your Apple ID is your
identity, but it's also your key
to communicating with Apple.
And for this release we've
made Apple IDs simple
and more powerful to use.
Xcode 5 now includes a new
Accounts pane to manage all
of the Accounts that
the ID will use.
Entering your Apple ID
gives you access to all
of the assets necessary
for App Store development.
And for those amongst you
who have multiple Apple IDs,
you can enter them all into
the panel here and select
which one you want to use
at anytime including
specifying them per project.
[ Applause ]
And to take things
a step further,
we've built some great
functionality on top of this
in the form of Automatic
Project Configuration.
Wrong button there.
Automatic Project Configuration.
So, with each platform release,
we give you guys amazing new
features and capabilities,
each with their own options and
also with some requirements.
And we wanted to make it
really easy for you guys
to get started with
these features.
So, we've built a section
of the Project Editor
dedicated directly to each
of these capabilities with
all the necessary requirements
and options in one place.
And getting started with
the feature is really easy.
It's a simple matter
of flipping a switch.
Doing so, let's extra -- make
all of the necessary changes
to set up your machine
for development.
That includes changing project
settings, adding frameworks,
setting entitlements, and
making all of the requests
and downloads necessary
for App IDs,
provisioning profiles,
and certificates.
[ Applause ]
From start to finish, you
can stay in Xcode and focus
on the work you want to do
and frankly let Xcode do
all of this work for you.
We wanted to provide also some
great source control features
for you to use.
And in order to do
that, we re-imagined
and redesigned our workflows
to integrate them directly
into the project life cycle.
In Xcode 5, you will find a new
top-level Source Control menu
with all of the options you
need and accessible at any time
in a really simple manner.
When you want to access the
project for the first time,
the new checkout workflow
makes that really easy.
Select the repository, select
the branch, and Xcode will check
out your project
and open it for you.
Now, once you have
the project open,
you'll notice the new working
copies area of the menu.
This provides a list of all the
working copies you have opened
in your project plus their
current branches, making it easy
for you to keep track of
what you're working on.
The Associated Branch
menu gives you all
of the branch management
functions you need,
such as creating new
branches, switching branches,
and merging right from
inside the project workflow.
And when you want more detailed
information about what's changed
in your working copy,
the Integrative History
View provides a browsable
and searchable display
that works across all
of your working copies.
For this release,
we've really focused
on giving you guys great
Source Control tools.
We've added functionality
to the editor,
giving you the preferences
and integrated Subversion 1.7.
So, for all of you not
using Source Control today,
I highly recommend you guys
give this new features a try.
Continuous integration.
For those of you not
familiar with this term,
Continuous integration is the
practice of taking changes
from many developers and
merging them frequently.
Ensuring the code
builds, your tests pass,
and that generally your
project meets your requirements.
By integrating frequently,
you can minimize the effect
of any individual change, often
known as integration hell.
Now integration systems need to
provide a myriad of features.
And they need to fit well
in your development process.
One item that is often missing
from these systems is
tight IDE Integration,
which you want are
continuous integration systems
that are an extension of
your development process.
In fact, you want them built
on the native concepts
of your tools.
And for Xcode 5, that's
exactly what we've done
in the form of bots.
[ Applause ]
Cool icon, even cooler
technology.
Bots are continuous
integration systems that --
well, bots are tasks and
they run on OS X server.
And their primary reason for
being is to do your bidding.
So bots use the Xcode
5 technologies
to perform integrations,
which are sorts of tasks
like build, test, and analyze.
And to get to what the final
-- the slide finally says here,
I'm going to show you a
demo of how bots work.
So here I have the iOS
version of a project.
Now, behind the scenes here,
my team has set up a Mac mini
and installed the
latest OS X server.
And we've created bots for all
of the projects that we're going
to use throughout WWDC.
For me to take advantage
of the bot,
all I need to do is add the
account to this Xcode instance.
So I'll bring up
my preferences here
and we see the new
Accounts pane.
I'll click the plus
sign and say Add Server.
Now we see that on my Mac mini
is broadcasting over Bonjour.
I can select that and I'll enter
my extremely secure credentials.
Now, when I click Add,
I want you to watch
in the left hand side in
the project navigator.
You see when I click
Add, a new item appears.
That's my bot.
What we're seeing here
is the log navigator
which normally presents
all of your local actions.
We wanted to integrate the
bot into the log navigator
so you could correlate what
the bot is doing for you
with all the work
you see locally.
Selecting the bot is going to
show me the integration summary.
And here it is.
And there's a lot of
information going on here.
[ Applause ]
Across the top, you're seeing
the integration results.
These are the kind of
statistics of the last run --
errors, warnings,
analyses, and tests.
We see I have zero errors,
so my product is
building successfully,
but I still have some issues I
should probably be resolving.
Across the middle of our charts
that display the relative
recent history of my bot,
for things like builds
and tests.
We can see that I've had some
warnings happen for a while.
We can see this integration
here right in the middle
with the red bar, that's
one that actually failed.
On tests I'm not
doing too badly.
The green are all the
tests that passed.
But it looks like we had some
failures introduced recently.
I should probably look at that.
Across the bottom are
the integration details.
These are the specifics of what
happens during this integration.
They might look kind of
familiar, it's very similar
to the style we present
them in the bill blogs.
And in fact they
work very similarly.
I'll double-click on our
olm here and it's going
to take me right to that
place in my source code.
Now I want to point
out what this is doing.
It's taking information
the bot gave me
and presenting it right
inside of my project.
So now I can change the
source code, integrate it,
and push those changes out.
So it's a really
great integration
between the two systems.
We'll go back to the
summary here and look
at some more information.
One of the really
valuable things
about the bot is doing
for me is testing.
And if I select the
Test tab across the top,
we'll see the test history
for all the integrations
that have happened recently.
Across the top is a timeline
that shows me my test history.
You can see my tests have
been building up over time,
but recently, it looks like we
had some tests not get performed
but it looks like
we're back on track.
I could actually grab this
loop and move it anywhere back
in time and look at the test
history to get more information
on a particular issue.
The bottom section is
showing me a combination
of pieces of information.
The rows are all of the
tests in my project.
The columns are the integrations
or the actions the
bot are performing.
So we can see here,
this is when some
of the tests were created
the first time they were run.
We can also see where
tests failed.
This column right here, this
is the integration that failed
and none of my tests ran.
So it gives me a great way to
kind of see how the evolution
of my project has gone.
Let's say we wanted
to investigate this
particular test issue,
well I have a couple options.
One would be to double-click
on it and navigate
to the source code like
I did before and try
to fix the problem myself.
Another option though would
be to look at the integration
and see who made the changes
and get them to fix it.
Well, I'll do that
one right now.
So to do that, I'm going to
double-click on the Integration,
and jump to the Integration
Details.
This is similar to what
I was saying before,
it's showing me the results
and it's showing me the
specific details below.
But there are some other
tabs across the top
that will provide
additional information.
I'll select the Tests tab
and we'll now see here are
the results from my tests.
Important thing to note here is
it's also showing me the devices
it was running on, this bot
is running all of my tests
on three separate devices,
an iPad and two iPods.
Now, my test is failing
uniformly across all of them
so it's probably
a logic failure,
but this would be a really great
way for me to be able to test
if different devices
cause problems for my app
or even devices running
different OS's how my tests do.
I'll select the Commits tab
across the top and look to see
who made the change
and up it was Max
who made this change,
so we can blame him.
Actually this is probably
difficult for you guys
in the back to read, but if I
read the commit message it says,
"Re-enable tests that should
have never been disabled."
If I wanted to figure out more
about what Max means by that,
I can just click on the Show
Modified Files, and it's going
to show me that very familiar
comparison view of the changes
for this integration and sure
enough looks like Max took
out some comments
for some tests.
We should probably
go and fix that.
But right here you can see the
bot is doing a bunch of work
for me, building, analyze,
testing and I can get
that information
right here inside
of the IDE quickly and easily.
So, this is just a little
bit of the power of bots.
What I'd like to show you next
is how easy it is to create one.
We already have one from
my iOS project here.
So, let's bring up the
OS X project I had before
and create a bot for this.
Creating a bot is as simple as
going under the Product menu
and selecting Create bot.
The first question it's going
to ask is what I want to build.
And this is going to
be a very familiar list
of all the schemes
in my project.
I'll select this one,
the project I want
or the item I want.
My servers are already
selected, and I'm going
to leave this box checked to
say integrate immediately,
we wanted to kick off and
start doing this work.
I'll select Next.
And I now have some
options for when
and what the bot does for me.
I can set the schedule to go on
periodically at a certain time,
manually at my request
or uncommit.
I'm going to select uncommit
because I want the bot
to do this work every time
someone makes a change.
I'll leave the default actions
checked, I wanted to analyze,
test and create an archive
of my project when it's done.
I'll select Next.
And the bot now provides
me access to send
out email notifications
when integration is
successful or when it fails.
I definitely want people to
know when they break something,
so I leave this check
box enabled
and we'll click Create Bot.
That's it, Xcode and the
server have not communicated
to create a bot for
this project.
And here it is it shows
out in my navigator.
So, just like that I
was able to make use
of the continuous
integration system
to start tracking my project.
Now, it's going to take a second
here to perform the integration.
So, in the meantime what I want
to do is show you some other
features we have in the system.
In order to keep track of all of
the projects you might be using,
we have an integrated web view.
You can see here a list of
all the projects that I have,
their current status and the
ability to interact with them.
In fact I can go ahead and
click on anyone of these
to create an integration
or download the product
of any of these bots.
So, this is a great way
for engineering, QA,
and other groups to leverage
the value and the power
of the continuous
integration system.
But to keep everybody kind
of on a level playing field
with how things are
working, we also want
to provide a really interactive
and fun display and we've done
that in the form of Scoreboard.
[ Applause ]
The Scoreboard presents
a view of all of the bots
that are running on my server.
On the left hand side
you can see the projects
and their current status;
on the right hand side
you can see the details.
Integration results the
commit logs and devices
that it was running on.
And you'll see that it cycles
through each one giving me the
details, it happens to hang
out a little bit longer on
failed ones which is not good
for me right now, but you'll see
when it actually switches
it will give you the details
about each including
who made the changes.
So, this is a great way whether
it's running on TVs or monitors
around your office, or just
running on your desktop
for you guys to keep track
of how the continuous
integration system is working,
the status of your projects,
and frankly who the heroes
and the villains are
in your own office.
And that's Continuous
Integration with Xcode 5.
[ Applause ]
So, bots and Continuous
Integration.
At the heart of this
solution is OS X server.
OS X server continuous deliver
powerful services such as mail,
calendaring, and wiki, and the
Xcode service now joins them
to deliver continuous
integration.
And running OS X server
is easier than ever.
The set of experience has
been redesigned and simplified
and in literally just a few
minutes you can have the server
up and running on your network.
Now the Xcode service leverages
many of the functionalities
and features of Xcode 5
including the Apple ID
integration, unit testing,
and source control features.
And layers on top elements
like Bonjour discovery,
repository hosting, and the
new web client, and Scoreboard.
The combination of these
features is a continuous
integration system
that you, your team,
and your entire company can
use to deliver great iOS
and OS X applications.
Xcode 5, we have a ton of great
features for you in this release
and I'm pretty sure you
guys are going to love them.
With Xcode 5 you should be able
to build applications better,
faster, and easier than ever,
and we're really excited
to see what you do with it.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thank you, Matthew.
All right.
So we announced three major new
products to you today, iOS 7,
OS X Mavericks, and
also Xcode 5.
They contained fantastic
new features for end users
and developers and we recommend
that you use the next few months
to get ready for us launching
these products later this year.
To get you started, you're
going to make developer previews
of all these products
available for you today.
So, you'll be able to go
to the WWDC attendee
website later this evening
and download previews of
iOS 7 for your iPhones,
iPads will come a little
later, OS X Mavericks,
Xcode 5 with the SDKs
for both of this new OS's
and even the new server app for
Mavericks which allows to try
out a new continuous
integration features
that Matt just showed you.
There will be numerous
opportunities here
at the conference to learn
more about these products,
we have done more than 100
sessions where you can learn
about what's new and different,
and many labs we have organized,
excellent opportunities for you
to meet within many [inaudible],
see you on site to get your
questions answered right here.
A few sessions that you might
find particularly interesting,
tomorrow we're going
to start the day
with the developer tools kick
off, and another session I'd
like to point out is the
maximizing battery life session
with [inaudible] tomorrow
who would tell you about more
about power consumption on OS X.
And with that I hope
you enjoyed the session,
I'd see you around this week.
[ Applause ]
[ Silence ]