[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Hi, I'm Jack Greasley.
I work for The Foundry.
And we make software to
do that sort of stuff.
It's a pretty cool job.
The Foundry was started about
15 years ago by two guys,
Bruno and Simon, working out
off a basement in Soho, London.
And they were making
image processing tools
for the local film and
visual effects industry.
Since then, we've grown a bit.
And we've really made a name
for ourselves by taking tools
and technologies out of
visual effects companies,
out of animation companies,
and commercializing them
and making them available
to everybody, so with tools
like NUKE from Digital
Domain and KATANA
from Sony Pictures Imageworks.
We've taken tools
and technologies
which were really only
available to the elite few
and made them available
to everybody.
One of the tools that we've done
that way is my particular
baby which is MARI.
And MARI is a GPU-accelerated
3D digital painting system.
And it was originally developed
at Weta Digital in New Zealand
which is Peter Jackson's
visual effects company.
I'm the product manager for MARI
but I'm also the
original author.
And what I'd like to
do is just take you
through just exactly what a
3D digital painting system
actually is.
When you're making a movie
and you're making a character
like Gollum here, he starts
off as a model, as a mesh.
And that model gives
you the overall shape.
It gives you the muscle
and the size of the object.
But it lacks the fine-grain
detail on the surface
that really make an
object compelling.
And it's the job of a texture
artist to go in there literally
with a brush and paint
in individual freckles,
individual veins, and
put the detail in there
that really makes it, you know,
go from a gray blank model
like this to something
looking pretty good.
And if any of you guys have
ever painted any figurines
or any models, you know just
how long it can take to get
that looking good and how much
detail you have to put in there.
So imagine that your model is
30-feet wide and it's going
to be projected on
a screen this size.
And this is the problem that
Weta Digital were facing.
How do you put enough
detail into your models
where the director can choose
to zoom into any part of it
and have it full screen?
In a game, you might put,
you know, one or two textures
on a character, and they
might be 1,000 pixel square
or 2,000 pixel square.
To get the level of
detail that they needed,
Weta Digital would often put
a patchwork of 500 textures
over the surface of
a single character.
And each of those
textures would be big.
It would be at least
2,000 pixel square
and sometimes much, much bigger.
And it doesn't stop there.
Those 500 textures only tell
you one thing about the surface.
They only tell you what color
it is, but you also need
to tell the system how bumpy
it is, how shiny it is,
how scratchy, how
dirty, how dusty.
And each one of those pieces
of information gives you
another 500 textures.
So very quickly you can be
up at 10,000 huge textures
for a single character,
and that can be 20, 30,
40 gigabytes of information.
And this was slowing
people down.
This was slowing
the artists down.
The one thing that artists
love to do is paint.
Things that they hate doing
are copying data around,
renaming files and
managing complexity.
And so, this is really
where MARI comes in.
I was hired by Weta
Digital in 2006 to work
with their texture artists
to really come up with tools
and technologies
to get them back
to doing what they
love which is painting.
So I got on a plane from London
down to Wellington, New Zealand
and worked with the texture
artists while they were working
on this little movie for
James Cameron called Avatar.
So my team and I were sitting
next to a room of fifty kind
of busy, kind of
caffeinated texture artists
for about four years.
And it got to the point where we
were releasing MARI three times
a day.
We'd do a version in the morning
and then fix it at lunchtime
and then another one
in the afternoon.
And if releasing three times
a day wasn't, you know,
enough work, my brand
new girlfriend
at that time was a
texture artist using MARI.
It took me a little
while to work out how
to prioritize her bugs properly.
[ Laughter ]
But I'm glad to say it worked
out and we're still together.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
So MARI was incredibly
successful at Weta.
Every tool-- so every model,
every character, every plant,
everything that Weta Digital
painted for Avatar was done
in MARI, and that was
several thousand assets.
Avatar did OK as well.
You know, I think three billion
dollars at the Box Office.
And MARI continues to be used
at Weta Digital until today.
Every movie that
they've released
since 2008 has used
MARI as its--
as their main texture tool.
So this includes things like
The Avengers, The Adventures
of Tintin, Rise of the Planet
of the Apes, and most recently,
this guy, again, for The Hobbit.
In 2010, Weta Digital and The
Foundry came to an agreement
to commercialize MARI.
So The Foundry licensed
MARI from Weta.
But what that really
meant is that they sold it
and they sold me along with it.
So I got on a plane from
Wellington, New Zealand back
to London which is 32
hours door-to-door.
And this time, I was
coming back with a USB stick
for the source code and an
invoice for The Foundry to sign.
My role at The Foundry
was simple.
We wanted to make MARI
the industry standard
for visual effects,
3D digital painting.
Over the last three
years, we've done that.
We've been incredibly successful
to the point that nine
out of ten of the
movies nominated
for visual effects
Oscars this year used MARI
as their main texture
painting system.
The only reason that
the tenth didn't is
that they didn't buy it in time
enough to use on the movie.
MARI is at use-- in
use at a whole bunch
of companies you
will have heard of,
so there's Industrial Light
&amp; Magic over in the Presidio,
DreamWorks Animations,
Sony Pictures Imageworks.
So really if you've seen a movie
over the last couple of years
in which there has been an
alien, a spaceship, a monster,
something blowing up,
you've seen MARI at work.
One of the really
great things though
about taking an in-house
tool something thats design
for one specific task and making
it available to everybody is
that you start seeing uses
that you never expected for it.
We've seen it cropping up
in games, in architecture,
in digital design, and even
in amazing artwork like this
which is from an album cover.
One of our most technically
innovative artists is a good
friend of mine called Scott
Metzger who works out of LA.
And he's coming up with
new novel techniques
for capturing digital
environments
and making photorealistic
rendering incredibly easy to do.
So what this really means is
Scott went out one weekend
and rented an industrial
laser scanner
and started scanning things,
and he scanned his apartment.
And he scanned it down
to millimeter accuracy.
And ran around his apartment
with a camera taking hundreds
and hundreds of reference
photographs making this enormous
dataset which he pulled
into MARI and used MARI
to paint those photos down onto
to this enormous
scan that he made.
And this created-- I think
it was a 20 gigabyte dataset
that he was able to
fly around inside
of MARI, edit in real time.
But it also meant that he could
make amazing photorealistic
renderings like this.
You can actually zoom down
into the work surfaces
and you can see fingerprints,
you can see fine-grained
detail in the paint work.
And this is an incredibly
useful thing
for the visual effects
industry and the film industry
because when you're
making a film,
what you normally do
is you build a set,
you put some cameras on the set,
you get the actors on the set,
you film it, and then the set
gets torn down and thrown away.
But what often happens
is two months later,
the director has this
flash of inspiration
that the thing that's
really going
to give him the Oscar this
time is a zoom through this set
which is now sitting somewhere
in a dumpster in Hollywood.
And these are called
pickup shots,
and they're incredibly
expensive to do.
You need to go and find the
bits of set that still exists,
you need to rebuild the set,
you need to reconstruct
the lighting,
you need to match
everything perfectly.
But with this technique, you
can actually capture the set
and its entirety, all
of the information,
all the lighting,
when you're shooting.
And when the director has this
amazing flash of inspiration,
it's then incredibly cheap
to do pickup shots rather
than incredibly expensive.
All of the examples
that I've shown
up until now have been
running on Windows and Linux.
But MARI was originally
developed for the first couple
of years of its life on
both Macintosh and Linux.
Unfortunately, as I mentioned,
we were releasing
three times a day
and maintaining six builds a day
in full production was really
more than we could deal with.
So we concentrated
on Linux at the time,
but I'm incredibly pleased that
MARI is actually coming back
to the Mac later this summer.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
We've been developing on
and targeting common
generation Mac hardware.
And partially this
is really selfish.
I want to demo on my brand new
shiny retina Macbook Pro and not
on a big ugly laptop
I've got at the moment.
The porting process for us has
been pretty straightforward.
It's really just
some housekeeping.
We need to take MARI's
OpenGL usage
because it really is
fully OpenGL based
and update it to
3.2 core profile.
This is something
we've been meaning
to do for a while anyway.
It really gives us a
lot of benefits in terms
of performance, speed,
simplicity of code
and stability.
And it's taken us
about six weeks to go
from absolutely nothing, MARI
didn't compile on the Mac,
didn't run on the Mac, to
being able to demo here today
which you guys will be
seeing in a few minutes.
The screenshots you can see
on the screen were taken
about a week apart
by my developers
as they were bringing MARI up.
The first image is the
first time MARI ran
on the Mac in five years.
The second one is a week later.
We have rendering
up and working.
And the third one is a week
after that where we're dealing
with big datasets we can
paint and we can animate.
So it really has been a
pretty seamless process.
However, we have been incredibly
lucky during this whole
process-- have been given
access to the new Mac Pro.
We originally designed MARI
with multiple GPUs in mind.
For me it makes so much sense
that you're going to want
to be processing
huge amounts of data
on one device while you're
displaying it fluidly
at 60 frames per
second on a second.
However, we've not really
ever seen a viable platform
for us to do this before.
We don't see multiple
GPUs installed
in visual effects
artist machines.
We see it in the
gaming world, you know,
people who put two GPUs
in their gaming rig
so they can play Gears
of War at 1080p 60 hertz.
But that power has never
been available to artists.
The multiple GPUs in the new
Mac Pro especially combined
with the updated OpenGL
and OpenCL support makes
it just a dream platform
for us to develop on it.
It's been really a
fantastic experience.
It's also going to make
my life a lot easier.
A large part of my job
is actually working
with our most demanding
customers to help them design
and build systems that
will meet their, you know,
incredible requirements.
I often get emails in the
morning along the lines of,
"So Jack, we tried to load
250 gigs of data into MARI
and it's running a
little bit slowly.
What can we do?"
So this machine is going to
make my life really easy.
I can say, "Go buy
the new Mac Pro."
[ Laughter ]
I can genuinely say it is the
best out-of-the-box experience
I've ever seen with MARI.
In terms of our most
demanding customers,
I think Pixar Animation Studios
are right up there with them.
I love working with
them as a company
because they represent
this amazing fusion
of being deeply artistic
but at the same time
being deeply technical.
Pixar were a very--
early adopter of MARI.
And we've been working with them
for the last, about three years,
to integrate MARI
into their pipeline
to put together new techniques
for creating incredibly
realistic characters
for their upcoming movies.
We're very lucky to have
Jonathan Hoffman here today
who's a shading technical
artist from Pixar.
Using MARI on the new Mac Pro,
he's going to be giving us a
sneak peak behind the scenes
into the process of how Pixar
design and build the characters
that are going to their movies.
But before we do that, I think
we should have a quick look
at some of the amazing work
that they've been up to
for the last couple of years.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
&gt;&gt; Tonight we party
like scarers!
&gt;&gt; I want to piece
of that action.
&gt;&gt; My friends call me Sully.
&gt;&gt; Mike Wazowski.
I'm officially a
college student.
Yeah!
&gt;&gt; We don't need to study
scaring, you know, do it.
&gt;&gt; That is a good point.
&gt;&gt; What's so scary about
a little librarian?
&gt;&gt; A bunch of guys went
to the hospital last year.
&gt;&gt; You can totally die.
&gt;&gt; And it's worth it.
Let the animal out!
&gt;&gt; Is that legal?
&gt;&gt; I've never seen him
this way in my life!
&gt;&gt; Trust me when I say
you are not going to want
to touch this bad boy.
&gt;&gt; I want to touch it.
&gt;&gt; Yeah, I want to touch him.
&gt;&gt; Hey, what are
you doing up there?
&gt;&gt; I can't go back to jail.
&gt;&gt; I'm going to rule!
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Obviously a lot of work goes
into every one of our films.
It's truly a collaborative
effort between hundreds
of really talented people.
What I'm going to talk to you
about today is really only one
small part of the whole process.
You saw on the trailer,
there are a lot
of different characters
in this upcoming film
and each character presents its
own unique set of challenges.
With Monsters University,
obviously since this is a
prequel, we're going back
to the world of Monsters Inc.
which we haven't
been to since 2001.
And recreating that world, you
know, we wanted to stay true
to the essence of the design
while still pushing the limits
of what we can do
now that it's 2013.
Obviously the technology has
come a long way since then.
Our two primary characters
in this film are still Mike
Wazowski and James Sullivan
from Monsters Incorporated.
Now, since this is
their college days,
we needed to redesign
the characters to look
like teenagers, and that
might be more difficult
than you would think because how
exactly does one make a walking
eyeball look younger, right?
You don't normally think
about this sort of thing.
But the people in the art team
did an amazing job in figuring
out and envisioning, you know,
how you take these monsters
and make them look younger.
With Mike Wazowski, this image
by our production designer,
Ricky, is this great
progression of Mike all the way
from toddler to adulthood.
And this is the final design
for both of the main characters.
And there's a lot of
real subtle things here.
I'm going to kind of show you
some of the things that they did
to make them look younger.
With Mike Wazowski, you know,
we took lots of pictures of all
of the people of the
studio and looked at them
when they were teenagers
and then looked
at their adult pictures.
And we learned a few things,
you know, besides, you know,
we all are, you know, little
bit less hair, you know,
some things like that.
But with teenagers, teenagers
reach their adult height way
before they really fill in.
And so with Mike, you'll
notice he's the same height
as he was before.
His limbs are the same length.
His hands and his feet
are the same size.
But he's a lot skinnier, right?
He's lanky.
And there's a lot
of other things too.
The colors are much more vibrant
and saturated to give them
that sort of youthful glow.
The horns are shorter
and more blunted because,
obviously as you get older,
your horns get longer.
And with Mike, you know,
you've got this great detail
of that retainer just coming
out of high school, you know.
I'm sure a lot of you
had to deal with that.
And then with Sullivan,
my favorite detail is he's
got this great bedhead look.
But since it's all over his
body, it's his bed-body look.
It looks like he just
rolled out of bed and all
of his hair is disheveled.
So a lot of thought and
time and effort goes
into really making these
character designs perfect
for these characters,
to really stay true
to that original design
but really take them
in a new direction
for this film.
But for every main character,
for every, you know, for these--
our core characters,
we need a good foil,
we need a good antagonist
for the story.
And so, I'm going to
introduce you to the character
that I have the chance to work
on for this film and I'm going
to show you a never before
seen clip from the movie
to introduce that character.
&gt;&gt; Please, let me
try the simulator.
I'll surprise you.
&gt;&gt; Surprise me?
I doubt that very much.
&gt;&gt; All right, so that
is Dean Hardscrabble
of the Monsters University
School of Scaring.
Now, she is the scariest
monster on campus.
And she is a scaring legend.
And with a character like
this, where does it start?
How does a character go
from start to finish?
Where does it begin?
Well it starts with
a bunch of drawings.
The art team does hundreds
of drawings for weeks to try
and really figure out
what a character is,
to experiment with
different ideas.
And with Hardscrabble, they
had a very challenging goal.
They needed her to be
very poised and elegant
and have this sense
of authority.
But they also needed
her to be terrifying.
And they were trying a bunch of
different ideas but it wasn't
until they saw this video
of a Amazonian centipede
which these things are huge.
It's a giant Amazonian
centipede.
They saw this video and
it had this amazing grace
to it despite the fact
that the first things
that you see is "Wow,
that is scary.
I'm going to"-- you know, if you
see that you want to run away.
But you see it and it had this
movement, this deadly grace
to it, and that is
exactly what they wanted
for Dean Hardscrabble.
So the director, Dan Scanlon,
drew the centipede tail
onto the back of Hardscrabble
and they realized
that is the design.
That was the central
part of her visual look.
So this is the final design by
Jason Deamer and it really--
the central figure of the
design is that centipede,
but then he's incorporated all
these other really scary animals
into that design.
She's got these bat wings, the
sort of dragon/lizard head.
And this, you know,
this was the character
that they've been searching
for, this elegance and grace,
authority along with
this idea of being very,
very scary and terrifying.
The first film, we had a--
you know, we had this cast of
very candy colored characters,
these very bright, you know,
and saturated characters.
And with the next film, we
wanted to stay true to that.
But with Hardscrabble, we needed
to make sure that she still fit
in the world of all these
other characters and
yet was still scarier.
In Monsters Incorporated, if
you remember the character
of Waternoose, he was
a little bit different.
And so we were trying to go
for something similar to him
where he still fit in the
world but was different
than all the other characters.
She again needed to be
scarier and yet still feel
like she came from
the same planet.
So once the design is settled,
it really gets passed in to kind
of two different areas.
The first is the modeling
department where, in this case,
Michael Honsel took this
design and began to sculpt it
on the computer, very much
how he would sculpt an object
in real life in real clay.
But he's sculpting it
digitally on the computer.
But it also gets passed to the
art department again to start
to develop the textural
look of the character.
And so this is a painting by
Shelly Wan and it was given
to me to show me,
OK, this is the way
that the surface should look
when it's reacting to light.
This is how the character
needs to look
in color and with specularity.
And I'll explain some of
the details of that later.
And so we've got
this beautiful image.
And along with this image comes
a bunch of reference photography
of the different creatures that
make up what Hardscrabble is.
And so, we we start with
her makeup, you know,
and all these little
great details
about what her face makeup
is going to look like.
But then we moved into
her different aspects
like the horns, how those
are going to be shaped,
what the colors are going
to be, how shiny they are.
And we go through
all of these details
of these different aspects.
But one of the things about
her shells and her legs,
with a centipede that's only
this big, I mean only this big,
it has this sort of
translucency to it
but that would give her a
sense of being very small.
So instead of going with the
insect variety of shells,
we went with more
of a crustacean look
because that would indicate
a larger scale creature.
So we have these great images
of her legs, of the shells,
and also these great
batwings and the translucency
that we could get
with the batwings.
All these things
were thought about.
But with this photography-- with
these images, I wasn't supposed
to take them and make a
photorealistic character.
The goal at Pixar is never to
go with just loads and loads
of detail and just make
it look like a creature
because we've hit this area
called "Uncanny Valley".
It's something we try to avoid
very much where you've added
so much detail that it
looks too realistic.
And at Pixar, we want to find
the essence of these designs.
We want to boil it down
to its simplest idea
and then really pull
that idea out.
And so with all these
photography, I was supposed
to take inspiration
but not copy exactly.
I was supposed to
find that simple idea.
So, the next thing
that we're going
to do is actually demonstrate
the process of how I began
to paint this character
on the computer.
Now, bear with me
because this is, you know,
the new Mac Pro,
it's unreleased.
We're running on an unreleased
OS and the software, MARI,
has only been on the
Mac for about six weeks.
So, what could possibly
go wrong, right?
So it'll be exciting
for me, hopefully,
exciting for you
as well to do this.
So, all right.
So this is the new Mac Pro
and this is MARI running
on the new Mac Pro.
And this is how I get the model
from the modeling department.
It's gray.
It doesn't have any detail
yet because it's my job
to add the detail
to the character.
So I'm going to navigate around
and you can see, you know,
this is a 3D model
brought in to the computer.
And the first thing that I do
when I'm creating a character,
when I'm starting to
paint in the detail,
is I start with the big
details and then I move
into the smaller details.
So for her, I'm going to start
with the color and I'm going
to start with her base color,
basically her flat base color.
So she's more of this
color than anything else.
So this is where
I'm going to start.
And the first big read that
I got from that shader packet
that I showed you earlier
is that her horns are sort
of different material
than her face.
It's a darker shell.
And so, I'm going to
paint in a little bit
of that variation first.
And I'm going to be a little
bit rough and sloppy here
because I'm compressing
a couple--
I would at least want to work on
this character for a few weeks
and I'm going to compress
that into about 15 minutes.
So I apologize if I'm a
little bit sloppy with this.
So I'm grabbing a brush,
and this is very similar
to a program like Photoshop
where you have a bunch
of different brushes that
can do different things.
And I'm just going to
start painting right
onto this model if I can.
Let's see.
Again, live demo, I apologize.
All right, here we go.
So I'm painting straight onto
this model and you can see
that it's, you know,
accepting this paint
and I'm getting a nice
gradient towards her horns.
I'm just trying to
lay in, you know,
a nice amount of detail here.
I'm going to move the camera
and that paint is going
to be dropped onto the model.
So you can see it's
actually been projected
through the model here.
I'm just going to add a little
bit more from this angle.
Then I'm going to go in and
do a little bit more detail
on one of these horns.
Now, again, I'm trying
to lay in some
of the bigger base details
first and then I'll start moving
into the smaller details.
You never want to start
with small details.
And any artist will
tell you this,
"If you start painting the
eyelashes before you've really,
you know, figured out
the shape of the head,
you're doing something wrong."
So I'm starting with the
big broad strokes first.
And this horn, if you remember
that image from the lizard,
it had some really nice
striations that kind
of ran along the horn.
And so, I'm going to start
painting some of those in.
But I don't want to go-- I
don't want to go too detailed.
I'm trying to keep this--
these shapes graphic
and really strong here,
get that simple idea
without going into, you know,
all those tiny little
nitty-gritties.
So I'm just rotating
this around.
Now, you'll notice that
this feels very liquid.
It feels very smooth, right?
As I'm tumbling,
it's so responsive.
And this really feels just
like I've got an object,
a model in my hand and I'm just
turning it and painting it.
And the way-- the reason that
that's possible is two things.
First, MARI is very,
very slick at allowing me
to see all these detail.
But secondly, it's
really so responsive
because the hardware is
supporting it is so well.
It's just-- you know, I forget
that I'm painting on a computer
and it feels like I'm
painting in real life
which is exactly what
I want as an artist.
So I painted this first horn.
I'm relatively satisfied
with it.
As with everything, as an
artist, I'd want to sit here
and noodle it for an hour.
But I'm going to skip
ahead, not bore you
with painting the
rest of these horns.
So I'll just-- this is another
layer here that shows you,
you know, the same treatment
to all these other horns.
And now as I zoom back, you get
that first pass at her color.
Like if you were to see
her from this far away,
she looks pretty good.
This is the biggest
read of the character.
But her skin is way
too simple, right?
Every-- all skin
has variety to it.
It has mottling and
freckles and--
you know, even the most perfect
person has a large amount
of variation in their skin.
If they look like this,
they look like a mannequin.
So I'm going to start adding
in some variety to her skin.
And I'm not-- you know, I
don't want to go too far again
because I don't want to
make her look grotesque.
But I want her to look--
I want her to look old.
She needs to be sort of this
figure of wisdom and authority.
And so, I need her to kind
of feel like she's had some,
you know, had some years,
had some experience.
Not exactly sure how quickly
lizard, centipede, bats age,
but, you know, she's got to
look a little bit lived-in.
So I'm just going to add in some
basic variety to her skin here.
You know, MARI comes
with these, you know,
a lot of really great brushes
that I can kind of start with
and lay on some detail.
Add some freckles, a
little bit of darkening.
And I can put some stuff on
and then pull it off
if I've gone too far.
That's nice.
Paint some freckles in
the back of her neck here.
It's always interesting,
the back of people's arms,
the back of people's necks
always get a little bit dark
and I'm not sure if
that's because of--
you know, that you just
get more sun there,
if the skin is a bit
more aged in those areas,
but it always seems that way.
It's one of those
things you start staring
at people differently when
you've been painting, you know?
And on creatures and humans
and characters for a long time,
you just-- you're
staring at someone's--
you know, the back of their
leg for whatever reason
and they're thinking, you
know, "What's he doing?
Why is he looking at me?"
And it's just because there's
this really cool vein doing this
really cool thing.
And it's not, you know, I'm
not trying to be insulting,
it's just that I'm
fascinated by it, right?
Because I'm going to use it to--
on the next day when I'm
painting this character.
So, anyway.
I hope I haven't
offended too many people.
Anyway, so I'm OK with
where she is right now.
And I want to talk a little bit
about how MARI is
storing this data.
You know, Jack gave you
a really great overview
of what MARI does, and we're
going to get in a little bit
into the nuts and bolts
as I'm demonstrating here
without being too technical
because I don't really
understand all the nuts
and bolts.
So you can see what
I've been painting
on the left side is mirrored
over here on the right side.
And what we're looking
at here is a series
of slightly disturbing images
where the character has been
flattened out or kind of pelted
into these tiles, right?
And what these tiles represent,
each one represents
a single color image,
just like an image you
would take on your phone.
And these images keep
all of that color data
that I've been painting.
And they can be scaled
to whatever amount
of detail you need.
So for a video game, they'd be
down at like 256 pixel squared
which is pretty small.
But for a feature film,
you never know how much
detail you're going to need.
So these are actually 8,000
pixels by 8,000 pixels.
That's 33 times bigger
than an HD frame
from a movie, all right?
But the reason you need that
is because you never know
if the character is going to
walk right past the camera
and we're going to
see all of this detail
on one of these legs, right?
And that actually
happened in the film.
She walks right past the camera.
So we really need this level
of fidelity to make sure
that she holds up in any
situation that she shows up in.
So, the next thing I'm going
to do and the reason why I came
into this view is to show you
how I would paint her makeup.
And I painted on
the flat version
because it's a little
bit easier than trying
to work around the 3D shape.
But as I paint on the right,
you'll see that it
updates on the left.
So I'm going to grab this
great eye shadow color.
Now, a couple of weeks
ago, we had the wrap party
where the movie is-- the movie
is finished and we all go
to see it for the first
time and we dress up.
And my wife usually gets her
makeup professionally done.
But I told her, "Honey, I
painted makeup before, you know.
I do it for work.
It's not a big deal.
I can handle it."
So, I painted her makeup,
I painted her eye shadow.
I thought it looked
great, you know?
I thought I did this great job.
She looks in the mirror, was
not pleased with my efforts.
So, we ended up being about
half an hour late to the movie.
Well we made it before
the movie.
We're half an hour
late to the party.
So we made it for
the important part,
but I doubt she'll trust me to
do her makeup again after that.
I guess, you know, painting
on monsters doesn't
necessarily transfer directly
over to painting on humans.
Would never have guessed.
Anyway, so I'm painting
this sweet purple eye shadow
onto this character.
And you can see,
again, as I'm painting
on the right it's
updating on the left.
And-- So what we've got
here is basically two views
of the same thing.
So now I've done that, I'm
going to just go ahead and visit
on the other side of--
I've got another layer
that has her makeup
on the other side.
I always forget character
right or my right.
Guess-- I guessed right, great.
I'm not even going to
bother with her lipstick.
Painting lipstick for me is
like when your four-year-old
daughter tries
to paint her lipstick
for the first time,
I've never gotten past
that because I just
don't do it often enough.
Anyway, so we've
got her makeup done,
and her skin color looks good.
But it's still lacking
some that detail
that we saw from the packet.
Now, this is the color channel
and I've got some nice
variety to her color.
But with every character
in a 3D film,
there are multiple channels
that define different parts
of what the character
looks like.
So this is the slide
from the shader packet
that shows me what the
characters look like,
what the character's face
looks like in more detail.
And there's some really
graphic shapes to her wrinkles
and to the, you know,
the shape of her face,
more than just the color.
And so we would actually paint
that on a separate channel.
It would be on what we call the
bump or the displacement map.
And that's a grayscale
channel that defines
where the wrinkles go in
and where things bump out.
And so, I'm going to show you
how I would do that over here.
So, here we're starting with a
color and I'm going to switch
over to the bump channel.
It starts out with this--
you know, just this
gray solid image.
And the first thing I'm going
to do is flood in some texture,
flood in just this
basic leather variety.
Now, it looks good but it
doesn't have the specificity
that we'd really want for this
character to match that artwork,
that beautiful artwork.
So the first thing that I'm
going to do is actually bring
in a picture of an elephant.
So this is the side of an
elephant as you can see.
And I'm actually going to
use that to paint through
and get some wrinkles on the
surface of this character.
So I'm going to start
with her eye.
And I'm trying to find the right
angle to paint through because
with wrinkles, if you look at
some with really wrinkly skin,
none of the wrinkles
are arbitrary.
All of them flow exactly
where the skin would fold
and compress over time.
And so, I can't just
paint these willy-nilly.
I have to really make sure
that they are feeling what we
would call motivated, right?
That they would be--
they would be naturally
where the character
would be wrinkling.
Now, this is obviously
a made up character.
But the character still has
to feel believable, right?
If this character
creature were to exist,
how would she wrinkle
in her face?
So, I'm good with these.
I'm going to zoom out.
And this is one of my--
it's really one of my
favorite features in MARI
because I can get so much detail
so rapidly onto the character.
And so I'm just going to paint
some of these wrinkles in.
And again, since this is
the black and white map,
it's really hard to tell
it how this is going
to affect the final
look of the character.
And I'll get more
into that later.
But this is, you know,
this is where we start
from in getting a lot
of this detail in.
There's this great spot on
the texture that looks just
like forehead, if I can find it.
Right about-- I'm upside down.
There we go.
So the next image that I'm
actually going to pull in came
from a picture that
I took on my iPhone
from the Pixar parking lot.
There are these trees there.
You can the tire of
my car over here.
These trees there that spray sap
in all the cars for some reason,
and I'm not sure, you know, why.
But I was walking into work and
I saw the texture on the side
and I just stared at it,
like, you know, weirdo.
I'm like, wow.
That texture looks really cool.
I'm not sure what I'm
going to use it for.
So I took the picture and then
I realized it was actually this
really perfect way to transition
from the organic leather
on the front of her face
to the more hardened shells
on the side of her head.
So, I really loved it for
that particular purpose.
Though when I took the
picture, I had no idea
when I was going to use it.
Again, I'm trying to get sort
of this material transition
because we're talking about
two different textures here.
This, again, is one
of my favorite parts
because I can really paint in
as much detail as I would like.
Now, so we've got these shapes
and it's starting to feel good
but it's still in the realm
of being a bit too
photorealistic, right?
We could be moving into Uncanny
Valley here if I'm not careful
with all of this photo
detail that I'm using.
And so, the next thing that
I would do is actually start
to paint on top of this
to really nail the details
down the way that-- the way
that it was in the art packet.
So, let's see.
I remember from the packet there
were these really graphic shapes
around her eyes.
I'm going to try
and pull those out.
Again, like I said, I'm
going pretty darn fast here.
So, I apologize I'm being a
bit sloppy in how I do this.
Once I've painted kind
of on top of this,
it starts to make
it feel more graphic
and make it feel a
bit more painterly
and less creature-shop.
I'm just trying to get
in some of these folds.
I'm going to get some
great crow's feet
on the side of her face.
It's funny because, shaders,
we always love to work
on old characters because their
faces really tell a story.
You can see, you know, the most
common expression a person has
had for their whole life.
You know, if you frown a
lot, those lines are kind
of etched permanently
into your face.
And with older characters,
I actually get to take part
in telling the story by what
the character looks like.
And that was-- you know, my goal
here is I-- with Hardscrabble,
I really wanted her to look
as good as this character was,
I mean, because she's
such an awesome character
and I really wanted to take
part in telling that story
and make her look visually
as cool as I possibly could.
So this is good enough for
now, a good starting point.
So I've painted into
this bump channel.
And I can actually take
that channel and start
to use it in the color.
So when I visit that
channel here,
I can multiply the color
just like in Photoshop.
And we can start to see how
it will affect the final look
of the character.
But there's a whole
lot of other channels
that are needed for
the final look.
The first is the
specular channel.
What this is, and I'm not going
to bother painting it today,
what this is, is it's showing
where the shininess is,
if that makes any sense.
It's showing what
parts are going
to be shinier than other parts.
And then the roughness channel,
which makes it even less sense,
is showing how glossy
or how rough those specular
highlights are going to be.
Now, as an artist, these
things don't make a whole lot
of sense to me visually.
I look at this gray
and I'm like, "OK.
What does that mean, right?
Her eyes are black.
Her lips are a slightly
darker gray than her skin.
Her color is this other gray.
I don't know how that
affects the final look."
And before a program like
MARI, I would have to load
up these channels as
individual flattened images
in a program like Photoshop.
I'd paint the gray her of her
lips and hope that it was going
to be the right shade of gray.
And then I'd kick off a render,
and that render would take
anywhere from two minutes
for a really kind of
inexpensive render
that shows me a vague idea
of what it's going to look
like to a full 12-hour render if
I'm going into the actual shot
from the film with all of the
lighting and all the bells
and whistles turned on.
So if I really wanted to see
how her lips looked in the shot,
I would need to wait up
to 12 hours to see that.
And so, I'd paint my gray.
I'd save the image.
I'd kick off the renders.
And I would wait.
And then I get to render
back and I go like, "OK,
her lips are too
glossy," so I'd go back.
I'd paint a slightly
darker gray.
And then I'd send it and then
I'd realize I'd gone the wrong
direction, and now her
lips are even shinier.
And I'd wait another
12 hours, right?
So, you can see how
that iteration could completely
kill the creative process.
What MARI allows us to do
is it allows us to take all
of these separate kind
of nonsensical channels
and create a shader that we can
actually preview in real time
that lets us look at
what the final look
of the character is going to
be in that finished render.
And instead of waiting for
anywhere from 2 minutes
to 12 hours, we can see that
at 60 frames per second.
So I'm going to switch
over to her shader
and turn on the lighting.
And you can see here
how now we've got all
of those different channels
that I've painted
working at the same time.
We've got those bumps that I
just painted, those wrinkles.
We've got the color.
And then the shininess, you
can see how her eyelid is much
shinier than the
rest of her skin.
And this is, you know, this
is possible, you know, again,
through the hardware and the
software working together
to give us this image.
And if you think about it,
remember how I said that each
of those frames was
8,000 pixel squared.
Well there's nine of those
for every single channel.
So for one channel,
the color channel,
that's 600 million
pixels, all right,
600 million points
of image data.
Now we're looking at four
channels simultaneously which is
about 2.4 billion
pixels, all right?
That is a vast amount of data.
That's 10 gigabytes
of image data.
And MARI is letting us
preview that all in real time
and it's running so
smoothly on this hardware.
I've been working on MARI for
about two or three years now
and I've never seen
it run smoother
than it does on the new Mac Pro.
By the way, so I've been
working on this for a couple
of weeks now and it's
been in this giant box.
I had no idea what it looked
like until yesterday, all right?
No idea.
[ Applause ]
The funny thing was it could've
been the size of a mini fridge.
I had no idea.
Or an iPhone.
We were thinking it was this
floating sphere, you know.
I had no idea.
But I just knew that it
was running really well.
I just had no idea it was
inside this mystery box.
So, it was just as exciting for
me yesterday as for you guys.
Anyway, I lost my
train of thought.
So here we are.
We're looking at
all these shaders.
Now, the great thing is even
though it's really pretty
to see this shader in real time,
here's where the actual
real advantage comes in.
Working at an animation studio,
you paint all these details
and then the animators
have to come in
and start moving
stuff around, right?
I mean the audacity of that.
So, I paint the wrinkles on her
and then once the character
actually is talking and moving,
sometimes what I painted
doesn't look right anymore
and I have to fix it.
Now, in the past, it's really
hard to identify those problems
or at least it takes
a lot of time
because to render the animation,
I definitely need to wait
at least a few hours
to see that.
And if I want to see it in
the context of the shot,
I would need to wait
up to 12 hours.
So, MARI allows us to bring the
final animation from the shot
into this environment so
I can actually preview it.
So, I'm going to scrub
to her animation here.
And this is the same
shot that I showed you.
And you can see her
speaking and moving around.
And I noticed at this point
where she raises eyebrow like,
wow, OK, my textures are
stretching right there,
all right?
So let me fix that.
So I'm going to go
to my bump channel.
I'm going to pull in my
elephant texture again.
And I'm going to
grab these wrinkles.
And I can paint straight
onto this animated frame,
right, in real time.
[ Applause ]
It's pretty cool, huh?
And now when I play the
animation, I can say, "OK,
you know, how does it look, you
know, at this moment, right?
How does it look, you
know, at any given frame?"
And I've just identified
and fixed a problem
in about 30 seconds that
would've typically taken me
about 2 days before if I
were to wait for the full--
all the bells and
whistles renders, right?
And that is fantastic.
It is-- you know, I'm able
to work ridiculously faster
in an environment like this.
And it is, you know,
again-- so, like I said,
MARI has never run faster than
I've seen it on this machine.
And we can push the
limits of that.
So, this character represents
about 10 gigabytes worth
of image data but we
can do more than that.
I can bring in Mike Wazowski
which essentially doubles it
to about 20 gigabytes
because he's got his own set
of textures.
And so he's over here, right,
and we can preview
his animation as well.
So he's saying, "Please,
let me try the simulator.
I'll surprise you."
[ Laughter ]
So there he is.
And we've got both of these
characters and I can see them
in context together, right?
I can see them right here
and that is so helpful.
It's so amazing to be able to
find and identify any problems
that we have by having
these characters
in the same room together.
And I can even bring
in the set and see them
with their shadows
in this environment.
And it's been so amazing.
And, you know, I think
that's it for the demo.
I've-- it's been such a
privilege to speak to you today
to able to work with
this amazing hardware.
I can't wait to get
my hands on one.
I can't wait 'til the fall.
And I've been so-- it's been
such a privilege to work
on Monsters University.
We're really proud of this film.
And I hope that all of you guys
go see it because it's amazing.
We're going to end with
another trailer from the movie.
And, yeah, let's go to that now.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; [Background Music]
Welcome to the Scare Floor.
&gt;&gt; Wow.
&gt;&gt; How do I become a scarer?
&gt;&gt; I'm officially
a college student!
Mike Wazowski.
&gt;&gt; James P.
Sullivan.
&gt;&gt; Like Bill Sullivan?
&gt;&gt; He's my dad.
&gt;&gt; I expect big things from you.
&gt;&gt; I just need to ace my
classes, graduate with honors,
and become the greatest
scarer ever.
&gt;&gt; Help!
[ Noise ]
&gt;&gt; Were you kissing my hand?
&gt;&gt; And what about you
with all your shedding.
&gt;&gt; I don't shed.
&gt;&gt; Really?
&gt;&gt; The star player
has just arrived.
&gt;&gt; You're my hero.
&gt;&gt; Yeah!
&gt;&gt; Slow down, squirt.
&gt;&gt; This is a party
for scare students.
&gt;&gt; I am a scare student.
&gt;&gt; I mean for scare
students who actually,
you know, never change.
&gt;&gt; Just wait hotshot.
I'm going to scare circles
around you this year.
[ Noise ]
&gt;&gt; My brothers appose
my [inaudible].
&gt;&gt; [Inaudible] everybody
let's keep a dream journal.
&gt;&gt; I'm a dance major.
And I'm not.
&gt;&gt; Not exactly the
scariest group in the world.
&gt;&gt; Smile!
&gt;&gt; Hi mom!
[ Laughter ]
&gt;&gt; I thought I could
show everybody
that Mike Wazowski
is something special.
&gt;&gt; Just reach deep down
and let the scary out.
&gt;&gt; Boys, oh, scary.
&gt;&gt; Up top.
&gt;&gt; The whole school
is finally going
to see what Mike
Wazowski can do.
&gt;&gt; Time to go to work.
&gt;&gt; Scary feet, scary
feet, scary feet.
The kid's in the bathroom.
[Shouting]
Angry poodle.
Dance clown.
My Aunt Phyllis.
In the morning.
&gt;&gt; Shhh! Quiet.
&gt;&gt; What's so scary about
a little old librarian?
&gt;&gt; I said quiet!
&gt;&gt; Move it!
Move it! [Shouting]
[ Music ]
&gt;&gt; I want to piece
of that action.
&gt;&gt; Tentacles and
serpent's wings, they-- ugh!
&gt;&gt; Can't wait to start
scaring with you brothers.
&gt;&gt; We're going to
hit you to pieces.
[ Music ]
&gt;&gt; Stop doing that.
&gt;&gt; Have fun kids.
I'll just be here
listening to my tunes.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; OK. So thank you very much to
Jonathan and thank you very much
to Apple for the opportunity
for being here today.
And thank you for
being here to watch.
Thank you.
&gt;&gt; Thanks for coming.
[ Applause ]