[ Silence ]
&gt;&gt; Morning.
Everyone hear me?
All right, welcome to
Efficient Design with XPC.
Thanks for choosing Russian
Hill for your post-lunch siesta.
Let's get started.
So on the agenda for today, this
a talk that's going to focus
on performance and the two
dimensions of that are going
to be architectural
design and implementation.
And towards those ends,
we're going to be covering
some new features in XPC
and cover some more advanced
and more efficient usage
patterns beyond some
of the basics that you might
have been exposed to over time.
So last time we gave a talk
on XPC, it was WWDC 2011.
So, let's do a short recap.
XPC is combined service
bootstrapping and IPC.
So, everything relating to
getting a service up and running
and talking to it,
exchanging messages,
it's all in the same library.
And this enables you to
easily factor your app
into different services so that
one service can be responsible
for, say, network communication,
they can have additional
privilege levels,
things like that.
And they are all deployed
within the App Bundle
and they never leave
the App Bundle.
So why would you use this?
Well, separate address basis
provide some key benefits.
The first big one
is Fault Isolation.
So if you have a piece of code
that's going to be running
in your app, let's say it's
dealing with untrusted data
and you don't necessarily
want bugs in your parser
to bring down the entire app.
Putting in another process means
that if you do encounter
a bug parsing some
of that untrusted data,
you'll end up crashing, say,
the service but the main
app is free to try again
or display some UI
to the user saying,
"Sorry, I couldn't do this."
And also, on the other
side of this coin,
you'll have a different
set of privilege levels
for that same-- for
that service.
So your app might have a set
of entitlements for example
that allow it to,
say, talk to iCloud
or read the contacts database
but the service that's working
with untrusted data doesn't
necessarily need all of that.
So, even if there is a
bug in a parser to exploit
to get random code
running, code running
in that process will not be able
to really do a whole lot that,
say, the main app
would be able to do.
And this allows you to
design with the principle
of least required
privilege in mind.
And we also provide a
completely managed lifecycle
for all these services.
So, you don't have to worry
about spawning them yourself
or setting up an idle exit
timer so that they exit
in an appropriate time.
We completely manage
all of it for you
and there's a lot less
boilerplate for you to write.
So we have two ways that
XPC is kind of exported
to you, the developer.
The main one is Bundled
Services.
These are the things that
we were just talking about.
They ship in the app.
They never leave there.
They're completely--
they're meant
to be basically stateless
on-demand helpers that come
up to do something, maybe a
service, few more request,
and can then be reclaimed
by the system later.
And that's part of that
fully managed lifecycle.
And this is the supported
way on the App Store
to have multiple processes
running in your application.
We also support launchd services
so that you can XPC to talk
to a launchd job that
you put on the system.
But this requires an additional
step for installation.
You have to have
the launchd plist
in either Library LaunchDaemons
or Library LaunchAgents.
And so the App Store
does not like that.
We want everything to
stay in the bundle.
So you can actually
use this part
of the technology on the Store.
But if you have a Gatekeeper
app or you're a sysadmin,
it's still useful for you.
So all of this means a little
more boilerplate code for you
to write, but you do get
additional capabilities.
You can run as root for one,
which is not allowed
for App Store apps.
And you can also run
your code independent
of the lifecycle
of an application.
So if you just have some
background piece of work
that needs to happen every so
often, you can use XPC to talk
to it, initiate it,
and get it running.
So here's what we provide today.
All of this is built
on top of libobjc
which is the Objective
C runtime.
So-- and XPC is very
heavily built on libdispatch,
and both of those kinds
of objects are actually objc
objects in Mountain Lion
and later so they can
participate in ARC.
And then way up in a space
somewhere is NSXPC connection
which was introduced
in Mountain Lion.
And that's a really nice set of
Cocoa APIs that aren't just kind
of like square bracket
wrappers for XPC.
They enable a lot of very
powerful Cocoa programing idioms
that we just really can't do
down at the libSystem Layer
where the C Library exits.
So let's get started by
talking about architecture.
So here are our architectural
goals with XPC.
The first one we want is to
avoid long running processes.
These are things
that just kind of sit
around on the system forever.
They might be listening
for an event.
They might be doing
periodic work.
But we would much rather that
they launch on-demand and exit
when they're not needed so that
there's no risk of them, say,
going crazy and starting
to consume resources
in the background.
We also want to be able to
adapt to changes on the system.
So, the system's resource
availability is changing all the
time when the user opens an app,
new sets of services come up.
The user might log in,
more users log out.
This means that memory, CPU
and Joules are all things
that are being shared across the
system and we want to be able
to say you-- you know,
you're part of a--
you're part of a collective
and we need to divvy
out these resources fairly.
And finally, we want
things to initialize lazily.
So this goes with
the on-demand theme.
In other words, don't do work
unless the user has actually
done something where you need
to initialize all of that.
So, you know, be as
on-demand as possible.
So the support list in Lion,
we have the technology called
XPC Events and this is kind
of a-- it's using XPC but
without actually having,
say, an app messaging you.
It's more like the system
is a source of demand.
And some of those demand
sources are IOKit events.
So, you can have a launchd job
that will kick off
whenever changes
in the IO Registry happen.
And we support BSD
Notifications.
So if you're familiar with
Notify APIs in libSystem,
you can just post a notification
and a launchd job kicks off.
In Mountain Lion, we
all-- sorry, in Sea Lion--
sorry, in [laughter] Mavericks,
we also introduced CF
Distributed Notifications.
So if that's your preferred
way to post a notification
and kick a job off on-demand,
that is now supported
by XPC Events.
And-- so, this technology
is really only available
to launchd services
because you need
to specify it in your plist.
So here's how that works.
So in your launchd plist, you
have this Launch Events Key
and you're going to specify
"These are the kinds of events
that I want launch
be on-demand."
In this case, we're going to
talk about IOKit Matching.
So here we have a dictionary
of all the IOKit
Events that I want.
In this case, it's just the one.
And this is, you know, my
company's device was attached.
And in this case, it's
just a matching dictionary.
So you're going to have the
product ID, the vendor ID
and the provider class all
in that matching dictionary
and XPC will implicitly install
this matching dictionary,
listen for it on your behalf,
and kick you off
when this happens.
And for Legacy reasons, you have
to add this IOMatchLaunchStream
key and set it to true,
just do that, I won't
explain why.
And once these events
are posted,
they need to be consumed.
And you consume them by setting
a handler and this is a lot
like a handler on
an XPC Connection.
So you just call this XPC set
of Event Stream Handler API.
And the first argument is that
com.apple.iokit.matching name
which says, "This is the
handler for the IOKit Events."
And then it takes a
dispatch queue and a block.
And the block gets
invoked on that queue.
And then once that
block has been invoked,
the event has been consumed.
And this event is treated
like an IPC message.
So if you don't consume
the event, say,
by not setting a handler,
after you'll exit,
you'll be relaunched
to process it.
In the case of the IOKit
Notification system,
each notification has a
payload that allows you
to extract the registry ID of
the thing of the node that fired
and then you can reconstruct it
and turn it into
an IO service T.
So we've taken this
idea of things
that can launch you
on-demand and extended it
to Centralized Task Scheduling.
And you interact
with this technology
through the XPC Activity APIs.
And what this let's you
do is schedule things kind
of on an opportunistic basis.
If you have some piece of work,
let's say it's a network fetch
or doing some random
housekeeping, you might not want
to have it happen now.
You just want it to
happen at some point.
You don't really care when.
And you'd rather
just the system--
leave it up to the system
and let the system
determine when a good time is.
And the idea here is to minimize
the disruption of this work
to the user experience.
So if the user is not
using the machine,
that might be a good
time to do some activity
that synchronizes a bunch
IO to disk for example.
And this allows us to more
efficiently utilize the battery
because we can take
certain tasks
that have similar
characteristics like, say,
run every 15 minutes, and
run all of those tasks
on the same 15-minute interval
rather than letting them run
on their own kind of
15-minute intervals.
And this is new in Mavericks.
So we have two basic
activity types.
There's maintenance and utility.
Maintenance and stuff
like garbage collection.
Let's say, you periodically
write some files out to disk
and you don't really need
to keep track of them.
These tasks are going
to be interrupted
when the user starts
using the machine.
And they're going
to be kicked off
when the user is basically idle.
We also have a utility
type which is stuff
like fetching network data.
So this task is more directly
important to the user.
So we're only going to interrupt
it when resources become scarce.
So the criteria by which
you can specify an activity
to kick off are things like
being on or off AC power.
Whether the battery level
is at a certain percentage,
whether the hard
disk is spinning
and whether the screen
is asleep.
So we can actually do your
work while the user is, say,
not using the machine but
it's plugged in to AC power.
That might be a great
time to do some--
any kind of indexing task that
your app might need to do.
And this is available to
launchd and XPC services.
And what's really neat here is
that it'll persist
across launches.
So, we can interrupt an
ongoing activity that you have
and then exit your process
because it's not a good
time to do the activity.
But then when a good time to do
the activity does come along,
we'll launch you
on-demand to keep going
and potentially complete
that task.
And everything just kind of
picks up where it left off.
So here's how you would just
create a basic activity.
In this case, the activity
criteria are specified
in an XPC dictionary and
we're going to set a few keys.
In this case, we
have an interval.
So we have a desired interval
of every five minutes
this thing should go.
And the grace periods, you know,
we have a 10-minute slack time.
So it's like we'd like every
five minutes but it's okay
to kind of play with
that up to 10 minutes.
And then we're going to set
this XPC Activity Handler.
So you just name your
activity, give the criteria
and then a Handler Block.
And the Handler Block delivers
the activity object that's being
invoked to you so
that you can figure
out which activity you're
dealing with, if you have many
of them, and where to pick
up after you left off.
So right now, we've
been invoked.
So we're going to get some
piece of data from somewhere
and then we're going to set
the activity state to continue.
And that just means that,
you know, yes, we're going.
And then, as the
activity is going,
we're going to dispatch Async to
the main queue to update a view.
And then once that block
completes, we say, "Hey,
now this activity is done
and you don't have
to do it anymore."
But if that block never gets
invoked for whatever reason,
let's-- and then let's say the
app is killed before it can be
invoked, we'll bring you back
and then you'll be invoked
with this Handler Block again
and you'll get another
opportunity
to try completing that task.
So that's what we
have architecturally.
This is how to-- this helps
you design more efficient apps
that play better on the system.
So, let's dive into the actual
ways you can use the APIs better
to get more efficient
performance.
Let's start by covering what we
have a service lifecycle now.
So right now, we have
an app and we have one
of its services there
on the right.
The app is going to send some
messages to that service.
The service gets
launched on-demand
and it starts doing stuff.
While it's doing this
stuff, it's protected
from sudden termination
which means that the system
under Memory Refresher won't
see that this is something
that can be reclaimed.
But, as the replies for all
those message got sent back,
you saw that that green
bubble kind of faded away
and that means that as soon
as the last one goes away
or as soon as the last reply is
delivered, the system is free
to reclaim that service again.
So we have the service
launched on-demand.
The system stops it as needed.
These conditions can
be Memory Refresher
or idleness and lack of use.
And we will also tear everything
down when the app quits.
So, Sudden Termination
as it applies
to XPC is automatically handled.
So since XPC knows when
you're receiving a message
or sending a reply to a
message, we can disable
and enable Sudden Termination
as we see those events
coming and going.
So in this case,
we get a message
and then we immediately disable
Sudden Termination for you.
And then when we see
that you've replied
to that message,
we'll re-enable it.
And as soon as all your
replies have been sent,
you're killable by
the system again.
So we've taken the same
idea and applied it
to something called
Importance Boosting
which is new to Mavericks.
And this is the default behavior
now for bundled services.
And what happens is that they
are background by default.
So whatever the service does
will by default not interfere
with any UI applications
that might be running.
But, if the UI application
does message that service,
the service's priority
gets promoted temporarily
to handle that request.
And the idea here is
with everything else is
to minimize the disruption of
your work to the user experience
if it's not directly aiding it.
So here's how that
lifecycle works.
It's very similar to how the
transactional lifecycle was
managed before.
So the app comes up, sends
some messages to the service,
and then the service
gets launched on-demand,
and now it's protected but now
it's boosted for that entire--
for all three of those messages.
And then once those messages get
sent, then the boost goes away.
And then any work after that
point, any work the service does
on its own behalf like, say,
from a timer or something
like that does not
interfere with the app.
The app will win any
resource contention fights.
So that's bundled XPC
services by default.
But if you have a launchd job,
you can also opt into this.
And we have a new plist key
called Process Type in Mavericks
that you can use on your launchd
job to opt into this behavior.
And once you've opted in,
it all just works
basically transparently
because through the same
mechanisms that we use
for tracking, sudden
termination.
We also have some other values
for that Process Type key.
Adaptive is the one we
would prefer that you use
because it means that you'll
only contend with apps
when you're doing
work on their behalf.
And this is useful when
you have a launchd job
that your app communicates with.
If the launchd job never really
needs to steal resources away
from apps on the system, you
can set it to background.
And this is useful if you
have a launchd job that's part
of the app but doesn't-- the app
doesn't really have a dependency
on anything that the job does.
So it's not supposed to update
its UI in response to something
that that launchd job is doing.
We also have this
Interactive key.
We'd rather that you simply
not use it because it will mean
that your service,
whatever it does,
can always potentially
steal resources away
from an application
and potentially results
in a stuttering UI.
And then there's a
Standard which is the same
as just not specifying
something.
So if you really just
want to have this key
in your plist, use that value.
So, we do a manner of
Automated Boost Tracking,
but you might want to
persist your boosts.
So you might have a work that
is going on outside the scope
of what XPC can know about.
So when you get a message,
by the time you've gotten
the boosting message,
we've already applied
this boost to you.
And-- so if you want to persist
it, the first thing you're going
to do is create a
reply of that message.
And that means that the boost's
lifetime goes from the message
that you received into
that reply object.
And then we're going to do
some work asynchronously.
Since we're using
ARC in this example,
the reply object is
captured and retained.
And therefore, the
boost stays alive
until that reply object
goes out of scope at the end
of this block and then
the message gets dropped--
sorry, and then you
send the reply
with XPC Connection
Send Message,
and then the runtime
asynchronously sends the reply
behind the scenes.
And then when its final
reference gets dropped,
the reply-- when the reply
message gets de-allocated,
you'll end up dropping
your boost.
There's another pattern
where you might want
to say send multiple
replies to a single request
and also maintain the
boost for that duration
but the API only
directly allows you
to send one reply to a message.
Well we've got a--
there's a usage pattern
where you can actually do
this using multiple replies.
And you do that by having
an anonymous connection.
And to create that
connection, you just give Null
as the first parameter
to XPC Connection Create.
So once we've created this,
we're going to send it
to the other side to the
service in a message.
And it's just like sending
any other key or value.
We're just going to send
the anonymous connection
in a message key to
the key back channel.
And-- so once we've sent the
message, the other side gets it.
And then we're going
to setup our end points
to receive the replies
from that other side.
So once we've created
the connection,
we're going to set an event
handler on it and this is going
to be a similar kind of
event handler to the one
that you will set
for launchd's job
when you use XPC Connection
Create with MockService.
In this case, we're going
to say expect five replies
and we're going to expect--
or each invocation of this
event handler is going
to deliver a connection to me.
In this case, I'm only
ever going to get one
because I've only ever
sent it to one person.
So, once I get the new
connection in that handler,
then I set the message
handler on that connection.
And that handler gets invoked
whenever there's a new reply
to send to-- to be given to me
and I'm just going to do stuff
with that message and then
that function will tell
me, "Yes, I'm done now."
And if that's the case, we
just cancel the connection.
So on the other side, when it
receives the message containing
that anonymous connection,
it's going to extract it
with XPC Dictionary
Create Connection.
And then it just sets an event
handler on it and resumes it.
So this is only-- it's
only ever going to be used
for sending a message.
So we have an event handler
that all it does is just
cancel the connect ion.
And we need to have
some sort of reference
to the connection in that block.
Otherwise, there will be
an implicit cancellation
of the connection
because ARC will see
that the variable
has gone out of scope
in not referenced from anywhere.
So here's the interesting
part where the server is going
to send back however many
replies to the client it wants.
In this case, we're just going
to dispatch apply five things
on a concurrent dispatch queue.
And then we're going to send
them all to that connection
that we got out of the message
the same way we would send
to any normal connection
that we created with, say,
XPC Connection Create.
So we'll do stuff.
We'll populate the message.
And then we just send the
reply or the iterate of reply
over to the backchannel
connection.
And ARC will capture
that reply--
sorry, ARC will capture
that message object
in all five of these blocks.
So when the last of
them runs and gets--
and goes away, the message will
have its last reference released
and then your boost drops.
So we've also made some
changes to how large chunks
of data are handled in XPC.
The runtime recognizes
very large data objects.
And when it sees one of these,
it goes down a fast path
to avoid copying
as much as it can.
So what this means to you is
that there is now a path
you can take to make sure
that when you give XPC
a large buffer of data
that it is never
copied from the time
that you created data
object out of it to the time
that the other guy receives it,
and it's completely copyless.
So, how this works is that
we deal with the VM Object
that backs your large buffer
and then we just share it
as a copy-on-write
shared memory.
And this is a page
granular allocation.
So, you can't really share--
since we use VM memory sharing
to do this, you can't really
share less than a page
and you can't share, say,
one and a half pages.
So it has to be a page-aligned
allocation that you own.
So a VM allocation that you've
actually taken ownership of
and created and know
the characteristics of.
And here's why that
part is important.
So let's say we have a process
that wants to share some memory.
And let's say that this
memory-- you got it from malloc.
Malloc might have taken this
little chunk of memory denoted
by the green in that address
range and put it on a page
and then it gives out
that pointer to you.
Now, let's say that you
take that pointer and put it
in an IPC message to share
it to the other side.
The VM isn't going to just
share that green region there.
The VM is going to share
everything on that page.
And what this means is
that if you do this,
it will end up leaking random
heap data to the other side.
And since XPC-- one of
XPC's primary advantages is
implementing a more secure
architecture, this would kind
of defeat the purpose of that
since arbitrary code executing
in the other process would
have access to your heap data
or at least a part of it.
And there might be
a password in there.
There could be any
number of little gems
for a security attacker
to take advantage of.
So, now that we've covered how
you would safely share a piece
of data, let's dive into the
nuts and bolts of how you do it
or how you this with XPC.
The first step you're going
to do is create a
dispatch data object.
And there's a new destructor to
dispatch data that you specify
which is the MUNMAP Destructor.
And, this tells dispatch
that, "Hey, this was allocated
with either MMAP or
MockVM Allocate."
So, you can use this-- you can
use the appropriate destructor
to free it.
And, once you have that
dispatch data object,
you wrap it in an XPC data.
And since we're dealing
with objects in this case,
we're not copying
that buffer locally.
So, you're transferring
ownership of that large buffer
into the dispatch
and XPC subsystems.
So here's how you do it in code.
So we create that
dispatch data object
with the MUNMAP Destructor.
And we give it a buffer
that points to a large chunk
of memory that we've allocated
using MMAP or MockVM Allocate,
the two are equivalent.
And we just tell it the size.
And the target queue for
the destructor to run on.
In this case, it
doesn't really matter.
So we just use Dispatch
Target Queue Default.
Once we have that data object,
we give it to XPC Data
Create with Dispatch Data.
And then we just send
the XPC data object
in the message we've
completely avoided any copies
of that really large
memory region,
so it's been transferred
much more efficiently.
So this isn't just available
to the low level C APIs.
Also doable from the NSXPC
data-- NSXPC connection layer.
And this is now because
in Mavericks,
dispatch data is toll
free bridge with NSData.
So you can create a dispatch
data object and just cast it
to NSData safely to insert it
into whatever Cocoa
object graph you want.
There are some constraints
around this behavior
and that subclasses
are not going
to be toll free bridged here.
So if you subclassed NSData,
that's not safely
interchangeable with dispatch.
And you can't have
created this data objects
with No Copy method.
And when you did
create this object,
any of those following
deallocators will work.
They just basically say it's a
piece of-- it's a VM allocation.
So also new-ish in our
last big cat release,
we implemented a
message receive path
and since we didn't
have a talk last year,
we'll talk about it now.
Basically, this is
now a much faster.
When XPC receives a message,
it doesn't actually have
to create an entire
objects graph
out of that message upfront.
So the act of receiving
a message
in prior releases would end
up creating this big storm
of allocations and copies while
we unserialized everything.
Now, we just deal with
the message directly
in a serialized form.
And this let's you drain
messages really quickly,
you know, and just start
processing stuff asynchronously
as fast as you can.
So there are certain kinds
of messages that we do this--
that we don't do this for.
Mainly, those messages
are things
that contain out-of-line types.
So if you have like
a file descriptor
or a shared memory region
inside of the message,
then we'll unpack
it all upfront.
This isn't too bad
because the assumption is
that if you're sending one of
these objects in a message,
it's probably to avoid
larger data transfers anyway.
So, the cost of unpacking,
it is pretty trivial.
And you're not going to
send a whole ton of them.
So, they won't be too
damaging to your throughput.
You can also take-- there's also
things you can do that will wind
up forcing the slow path.
So, for example, if you
get one of these messages
and then you start-- and then
you say you want to copy it,
we have to actually unpack
the entire thing in order
to create a copy of it.
Similarly, if you use the
XPC Dictionary Apply Routine,
we have to unpack
an XPC object T
for every key value
pair in that dictionary.
So, that will wind up forcing
a full unpack of everything.
And same thing there,
XPC Dictionary Get Value,
it returns an XPC object that
you can retain independently.
So that will actually unpack
the entire value associated
with that key.
And so, what that means is
that if you have a
nested container inside
of that message object,
then we'll unpack the
entirety of that container.
And then finally, if you modify
the dictionary, which is safe,
you're totally allowed to do
that, but if you modify it,
we have to unpack everything
to get it into a form
where it's safely mutable.
So that's we have
new in the runtime.
I wanted to also cover
the issue of timeouts
because there's a
lot of disagreement
over the best policy here
with local machine IPC.
You might have noticed that the
XPC APIs don't actually have any
support for timeouts, and
this is very intentional.
They're just really not needed
in most cases of the API usage
because local machine--
so two processes talking
on the same machine
and two processes talking
on two different machines
are actually different.
So as software engineers
and as computer scientists,
we all like to try and
consolidate two problem spaces.
This is one area
where they're separate
and they really should be.
And the key differentiator here
is that the kernel is not flaky.
It's not like the network.
It doesn't just kind
of like come and go.
It's your transport medium
and it can actually make a
guarantee for message delivery.
So once you have this guarantee,
there's really no reason
that the remote server process
shouldn't always be responsive.
So here's an example.
Well, here's an example of
kind of the bad side of, say,
using a timeout in one of
the send and reply routines.
It will confuse the
expectations of the client side.
So, for example, if the server
end is doing a network operation
on your behalf, you might want
to attach a timeout to the reply
on the client side so that
the client says, "Well,
if I don't get a reply-- it
is a networking operation,
so if I don't get a
reply within 10 seconds,
then that's a timeout."
But what that does is it
confuses the network operation
timing out and the server
process having a bug.
So, it might be that the network
operation would've succeeded
but there's a deadlock in your
server or there are some sort--
or there's kind of
mismanagement of resources
that prevented the server from
sending the reply in time.
But those two conditions
are going to be expressed
to the client identically and
you as a developer might end
up shipping the app with a bug
that you didn't actually
know existed.
So, how would we
optimally handle this case?
Well, it's not that the network
operations shouldn't have
the timeout.
That's just kind of a reality
of network programming.
But you don't want the client
side to manage that timeout.
You want it to be managed
on the thing that's actually
doing the network operation.
So the server sets up
whatever socket it needs to do
that operation, attaches
the timeout
that it thinks is appropriate
and then if that's--
if the server sees that the
request has taken too long,
then that means it can return--
it will return a message
to the client that just has
like an E-timed out
error in there.
And so, the client
knows that, you know,
the server should
always be responsive
and if it didn't respond to me
then that means I have a bug
and I should investigate.
That being said, there
are cases where IPC--
local machine IPC timeouts
are actually appropriate,
but they're not really
terribly common.
Usually, those cases derive
from, say, hard deadlines.
And this is also when transit
time makes a difference.
So the time it takes to send
the message to the other side
and for the other side
to send the reply back,
if that actually
matters in your use case,
you might have a legitimate need
for a timeout on
the client side.
And usually, this will be some
sort of realtime application
where your timeout isn't
just completely arbitrary.
It's not, you know, 10 seconds
or my favorite number
or whatever.
It's actually derived from
a desired throughput rate.
So if you're measuring
things like frames per second
or samples of audio process per
second, then timeouts are needed
so that you can know that
an operation won't complete.
And if it can't complete
in that amount of time
that you've given it,
there's really no need
to keep waiting for it.
You can just move on.
But like I said, these are
not exactly common use cases.
So we don't really have
support in the API for timeouts.
You can also-- but using
the asynchronous APIs,
you can implement your own.
And I'm sure a lot of you
have figured that out.
So, let's also talk a
little bit about debugging
and what we've got in
Mavericks for debugger support.
The first big one is that Xcode
now transparently supports
debugging XPC services.
So, you can just take a
service, set a breakpoint
on the file that's associate--
in a source file that
your service uses,
and then you can run your app.
And then if your app takes
a code path where it talks
to the service and
launches it on-demand,
then those breakpoints that
you set will be honored.
You don't actually have
to do any other work.
[applause] Yeah.
So, it's important to note
that this functionality relies
on enhancements to
the host that we made.
So, it's only available
on Mavericks or later.
So, yeah, it just works.
And also nice, there's a
copy files destination now
for the XPC services
subdirectory in your app.
So, you don't have to
select wrapper directory
and then specify XPC
services anymore.
We also have a tool for
debugging, importance boosting,
and leaking of boosts.
So if you're running into leak
boost, there's this iptrace tool
that will tell you why you were
boosted and who boosted you.
So in terms of debugging,
just debugging tips, a lot--
what a lot of people run into
is they will set everything up
and they'll run their
app the first time.
And then, immediately, when they
try and talk to their service,
they get a connection
invalid right away.
That almost always indicates
that there's been a
configuration error.
You know, the service
isn't in the right place
or the bundle isn't
structured properly.
But when you see this, just a
couple of things to make sure,
make sure that the service is
a dependency of the app target.
So when the app gets
run, the service should--
sorry, when the app gets built,
the service should also
get built before it.
And then that service
product should be
in the copy files build phase
of your app so that it winds
up in Contents XPC
services inside the app.
And then the other
easy mistake to make is
that you might just be using
the wrong service identifier.
So the one-- the name of the
service that you want to connect
to is the CFBundleIdentifier
for that service bundle.
And sometimes that's
easy to confuse
because when you view
the info plist in Xcode,
it will actually be-- it
will have dollar, you know,
product identifier that gets
filled in at build time.
So, you want to make
sure that you're using--
you're identifying your
service consistently.
XPC is also defensive.
It's really easily offended.
And this is also intentional.
So, we do our best to detect
noticeable cases of API misuse
and then we abort the
process with that back trace
so that you can fix the bug
before actually deploying
your app.
And so, we'll do this when,
you know, we detect conditions
that will almost certainly
lead to data corruption
or where data corruption
has clearly happened.
Things like underflowing
the retain count,
if you're still using manual
retain/release on XPC objects
and just other examples
of obvious API misuse.
A lot of this is detailed
in the XPC Abort Man Page
which is in section three.
And you'll-- the
tell-tale sign for this is
that you'll see an illegal
instruction being issued
and you're process
will terminate.
So, in the case where you
got crash report that--
where this has happened,
you'll see stuff
in the applications specific
information telling you why
this-- why the process
was aborted.
But you might be attached to the
service or the app with LLDB.
In which case, you're not
going to get a crash report.
You're not going
to get applications
specific information.
But we provide a debugger
specific API called xpc debugger
api misuse info that you can
call from within the debugger
and that will-- the result
of that will be a pointer
to the string that
we would've printed
in the application specific
information of the crash report.
So here's what it would
look like in a crash report.
You just have the application,
specific information
and it says API MISUSE:
Over-release of an object.
So in this case, we called
XPC release more times
that we have references
to the object.
In LLDB, you'll probably
see something
like Program received
EXC BAD INSTRUCTION
which is the Mock exception in
this case but it maps to SIGILL.
And then from the LLDB
command line, we just do a p
and then call that debugger
API that I mentioned before
and then it will print the
string that's associated
that that API would've returned.
And if you're hounding
your syslog looking
for every little thing that's
happening on the system,
you might have seen a
message that looks like this.
This is what it looks
like in Mavericks.
In previous releases, the part
where it says assertion
failed says bug.
This is cryptic and--
to file a bug
because we now how
to make sense of it.
If you're curious, it's just
the program counter offset
from the beginning of the
libxpc image in the process
where we encountered some weird
error that we didn't expect
and that last part is the
error code that we encountered.
Like I said, we know
how to make sense of it.
If you see of these, file
a bug with that log line
and any other relevant
contextual information
that you have and we'll look
into it and hopefully fix it.
So, that's pretty much
of what we've got.
So for more information on
any of these technologies,
Paul Danbold is the Core
OS Technology Evangelist.
The documentation for
XPC, we have a full suite
of man pages in section three.
I'm sure there are some
great man page viewer apps
on the store if you don't like
viewing them in the terminal.
But I encourage you to read them
because they're very
well put together.
And we also have a full set
of HeaderDoc inside the
actual headers of XPC.
So, look in User
Include XPC and then all
of those public interfaces
are documented with HeaderDoc.
And then the Daemons and
Services Programming Guide
which is on the developer
documentation website covers
when you would want to use a
launch daemon and the lifecycle
of XPC services and
all that fun stuff.
And if none of these resources
can answer your specific
question or you still have
questions about things
that aren't covered there,
there's always the Dev Forums
where you can just ask us
and we occasionally check
the Dev Forums as engineers
and if we can answer
you, we will.
Relatedly, the debugging
support for XPC and Xcode
that I mentioned is going to
be demoed in the Debugging
with Xcode session and that's
in Pac Heights tomorrow at 2:00.
There's also a session later
today which also cover some
of the architectural
things that we talked
about like XPC activities,
centralized tasks scheduling,
and making more efficient apps.
And that's Building
Efficient OS X Apps.
That's in Nob Hill later today.
And that's it.
Enjoy the rest of
the conference.
[ Silence ]